good night everyone
各位来宾晚安
Lecture is about to start
演讲会即将开始
Please set your phone to vibrate or silent
请将手机条为震动或静音
Remind you
提醒您
This presentation is in progress
本演讲进行中
Please wear a mask at all times
敬请全程配戴口罩
and prohibit eating
并禁止饮食
video and audio recording
录影及录音
Do not use the flash when taking pictures
拍照时请勿使用闪光灯
Thank you for your cooperation
感谢您的配合
Academia Sinica's 112-year-old governor Cai Yuanpei's popular science award begins
中央研究院112年知事想驗蔡元培院長科普獎座開始
We ask Vice President Zhou Meiyin to host for us
我們請周美寅副院長為我們主持
Ask Vice President Zhou Meiyin to host for us
請周美寅副院長為我們主持
Dear teachers Ma, distinguished guests and colleagues, good night everyone
各位馬老師 各位來賓 還有各位同仁 大家晚安
In order to commemorate the 155th birthday of President Cai Yuanpei Gu
本院為了要紀念蔡元培顧院長155歲的名誕
So we are holding today this is the 2023 Governor's Vision
所以我們在今天舉辦這是2023年的知事想驗
Dean Cai Yuanpei's Science Popularization Award
蔡元培院長的科普獎座
So we are very happy and honored to invite you to the Institute of Earth Sciences
所以我們非常高興也很榮幸邀請到本院的地球科學所
Ma Guofeng Distinguished Researcher of the Institute of Earth Sciences
地球科學研究所的馬國鳳特聘研究員
come and give us a lecture
來幫我們主講
see this generation of light that initiates earthquakes
看到這個啟動地震的光世代
When the light first penetrates into the monitoring of the fault zone
當光先深入斷層帶的監測
this could be very interesting
這個可能有非常有趣的內容
Then we know that Mr. Ma graduated from
那我們知道馬老師是畢業於
Department of Geophysics, Chuo University
是中央大學地球物理系
Then at the Institute of Oceanography at National Taiwan University
然後在那個台大的海洋研究所
Study abroad after earning a master's degree
拿到碩士學位之後出國留學
Finally at Caltech
最後是在加州理工學院的
The Department of Geology and Planetary Sciences
這個地質與行星科學系
very special one
非常特別的一個
received a Ph.D.
拿到了博士學位
Return to Taiwan to serve after graduation
畢業以後就回台服務
Then enter Central University to teach
再進入中央大學任教
until 2020
一直到2020年
Transfer to this institute as a special research institute of the Earth Institute
轉到本院擔任地球所的特聘研究所
He is also currently the Chief Scientist of the Taiwan Earthquake Science Center
他目前也是臺灣地震科學中心的首席科學家
That's also the director of the Earthquake Disaster Chain Risk Assessment and Management Research Center at Chuo University
那也是這個中央大學的地震災害鏈風險評估及管理研究中心的主任
Mr. Nama's main major is in seismology and political mechanics
那馬老師的主要的專業是在地震學及政源力學
So wait a minute to hear him explain this to us
所以等一下會聽到他把我們解釋這個
These studies are able to observe earthquakes that are very relevant to us
這些能夠觀測到跟那些跟我們非常有關的地震方面的一些研究
His greatest contribution was the first observation of the thickness of the Chinese belt of a large earthquake fault
他最大的貢獻是第一次觀測到大型地震斷層的華裔帶的厚度
Then, quantitative calculations can be used to obtain the energy for generating earthquakes
然後能夠用量化的計算去得到這個生成地震的能量
then what energy
然後還有什麼能量
military research on earthquakes, etc.
軍向地震研究等等
We'll hear some research on this later
我們等會可以聽到一些這方面的研究
What about the research on earthquake disaster risk assessment?
那由於這個地震災害風險評估這個研究呢
We can take the results of academic research
我們可以把學術研究的成果
applied to related industries
應用到相關的產業
To reduce the damage caused by earthquakes
也要降低地震的災害損失
So this is our Academia Sinica doing basic research
所以這是我們雖然中研院在做基礎研究
But it is closely related to the current situation of Paiwai.
可是跟排歪目前的狀況是息息相關的
Teacher Nama Guofeng has received many academic honors
那馬國鳳老師曾經得到多項的學術榮譽
as early as 2000
最早在2000年的時候
Elected as one of the top ten outstanding young women of the Republic of China
當選中華民國十大傑出女青年
In 2011, he won the Taiwan Outstanding Scientist Award
2011年的獲得了臺灣傑出科學家獎
Received the 17th National Award from the Ministry of Education in 2013
2013年得到教育部的第十七屆國家獎座
Measure right as long as it doesn't matter
措施權只要不要重要的
and many other awards
還有其他很多其他的獎項
2019 was elected to the American Geophysical Union
2019年是獲選為美國地球物理學會的會事
2021 is the Year of the Earth Science Society of Asia and Oceania
2021年是亞洲與大洋洲地球科學學會的
These awards of an X-Ware Medal Award
一個 X-Ware Medal Award 的這些獎項
So now we're talking about today's lecture
所以我們現在今天的講座
I will introduce this to you in particular
會特別為大家介紹這個
Our so-called vibration research on seismic waves observed by Mitsusen
我們這個所謂的光仙觀測地震波的震動研究
can help us
可以幫助我們
The observation of this earthquake
這個地震的觀測
And then going deep into this fault zone can provide high-resolution seismic signals
然後深入這個斷層帶能夠提供高解析的地震信號
This is very important to our understanding of earthquakes
這對我們對地震的瞭解是非常重要的
Okay, now please give us a big round of applause
好 現在就請大家以熱烈的掌聲
Welcome Ma Guofeng Distinguished Researcher
來歡迎馬國鳳特聘研究員
Give us a special lecture today
為我們做今天的特別講座
Thank you Vice President for your introduction
謝謝副院長的介紹
Also, thank you, my friends, for your special attention.
還有謝謝各位朋友還有副職命特別關注
Thanks
謝謝
I am very happy to have this opportunity today
今天很高興有這個機會
Personally, I think it is in our seismological science supernatural
我個人覺得是我們地震學科學靈異裡面
very important for a new generation
非常重要的一個新的世代
Then I think each science is about 20 to 30 years
那我覺得每個科學大概是二三十年
There will be a new conversion into
就會有一個新的轉成
then i'm glad to have this opportunity
那我很高興有這個機會
when i was a doctor
我在博士的時候
Seismology from flat to broadband
地震學從宅平帶到寬平帶
How about when you are more senior?
那到現在比較資深的時候呢
Having access to this highest resolution material again
有機會又接觸到這種最高解析度的資料
Analysis with the current big data data
以現在大數據的資料方式來解析
Earthquake Science Content
地震科學的內容
then i'm happy too
那我也很高興
My idea has achieved a key breakthrough in the hospital
我這個構想獲得院方關鍵突破
support for this project
這個計畫的支持
Only way to get this job today
才有辦法得到今天這件工作
Well, this is actually a new attempt
那這個事實上是新的嘗試
Then I would like to take this opportunity to introduce to you
那我想說藉由這個機會跟各位介紹
We now have the development of a new generation of earthquake science
我們現在地震科學新的世代的發展
and why do we need this thing
還有為什麼我們需要這個東西
Of course, there are still many challenges in it.
那當然它還有很多挑戰在裡面
but i think it's the future
但是我覺得它是未來的
Towards that job, of course I am the main leader
走向 那這個工作當然我是主要的帶領者
But it takes a lot of teams to actually execute
但是真正要執行的話 需要很多團隊
Because it actually has a lot of technology in it
因為它事實上是很多技術在裡面
Not just data analysis Data analysis is
不是只有資料分析 資料分析是
Now let's enjoy data analysis
現在開始我們享受資料分析
But in the first two years it was actually a lot of labor work
但在前兩年事實上是做了很多勞力的工作
researchers of technologies that matter to our planet
那我們地球所重要的技術研究人員
they are very important roles
他們是非常重要的角色
Dr. Lin Qingren Dr. Gu Jinshang
就林青仁博士 古今上博士
And researcher Huang Xinhua
還有黃信華研究員
This is a very elite key figure in the whole team
這是整個團隊裡面非常精華的關鍵人物
Then it's me and Germany
那再的話就是我跟德國的
Especially Sabastian and Philip
尤其是Sabastian跟Philip
their instruments in europe
他們在歐洲這方面的儀器
They first lent us the equipment
他們先借給我們儀器
Let's understand what characterizes the whole instrument
讓我們了解說整個儀器的特質是什麼
So I am very happy to tell you today
所以今天很高興跟各位講到
Launch the Seismic Light Generation
啟動地震光世代
Then I believe that those who are doing
那我相信在做的幾位
It should be a little bit about earthquakes
應該是對地震都有一點涉略
So what I'm talking about may be more popular than general science.
所以我講的內容可能比一般科普的東西
slightly higher
稍微高一點
a little deeper
再深一點點
but i think
但是我想
This is a knowledge experiment at the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine
這是在中醫院這邊的知識想驗
and the audience may be more able to
也是聽眾們可能都比較能夠
what you want to contact
想要接觸的內容
So I will talk a little bit
所以我就講的稍微在
General science is a little deeper
一般的科普再深一點
Well, of course earthquake observation I just mentioned
那當然地震觀測我剛剛提到說
I am honored to be in
我很榮幸的在
When I graduated from my Ph.D.
我博士班畢業的時候
The result is that the entire earthquake becomes broadband
得到就是整個地震變成寬頻的
The observation is that I go from 1Hz to
觀測就是我從1Hz到
1Hz should mean from 0.01 seconds
1Hz應該是說從0.01秒
I can write it all down to 100Hz
一直到100Hz我全部都可以記下來
So this is what we call a broadband seismic network.
那這就是我們所謂的寬頻地震網
In fact, in the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine
那在中醫院當初事實上就是
Dr. Liang Wenzhong We started to promote
梁文中博士我們開始推廣
的 Broadband Array in Seismology
的 Broadband Array in Seismology
This is BATS
這是 BATS
At that time, I was in the Earth Institute of the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
那當時在中醫院地球所
He has been in seismology in Taiwan
他就已經在台灣的地震學
play a very important role
扮演很重要的角色
That is, whenever an earthquake occurs
就是只要地震一發生的時候
Whether it's the shock of all the boots
不管是所有靴尾的震動
or any earthquake in the world
或者是世界上任何一個地震
happened we can all remember
發生我們都可以記到
Well, of course it has something to do with the work of the weather bureau.
那當然跟氣象局的工作
Of course it's very close
當然是很密切的
From the Odds Bureau, it is of course more biased towards large-scale earthquakes
奇象局的話 它當然是比較偏向是大規模地震
Scale 4 Scale 5 It's gonna start doing some of these enouncements of earthquakes
規模4 規模5 它要開始做一些地震的這些enouncement
Its location may not be as precise as ours
它的位置可能沒有像我們那麼精準
But it needs to be within the fastest time
但是呢 它要在最快的時間之內
Tell everyone where the earthquake is and how big it is
告訴大家地震在哪裡規模有多大
But with the role of BETS of the Central Plains Earth Institute
但是以中原院地球所BETS的角色
It's just that I am very accurate for small earthquakes.
就是我如何的小地震都定得很準
Then my scale also has a certain scale relationship
然後我的規模也都是有一定的尺度的關係
Only then can I have a series of high-quality data for earthquake research
我才有辦法有一系列高品質的資料做地震研究
Then this high-quality data is not just a study of Taiwan
那這個高品質的資料就不是只是台灣的研究
is the world's earthquake science
是全世界 地震科學
Of course I think it's the same in every field of science.
當然我想各個科學領域都一樣
That is, earthquake science is a very international research science.
就是地震科學是一個非常國際型的研究科學
Because of the large-scale earthquake, the so-called large-scale is scale 7 scale 8
因為大規模地震 所謂大規模是規模7 規模8
Of course we don't want it to happen often
當然我們不想要它常常發生
but as soon as it happened
但是它一發生之後
The world wants to be able to share this material and understand its uniqueness
全世界都希望可以分享這個資料 了解它的特質
In particular, seismology is a very science of earthquake observation
尤其地震學是一個非常地震觀測的科學
It must have earthquake observation and disaster status
它要有地震觀測跟災害的狀況
The more refined we are
我們越精進我們
theories of our science
我們的科學的理論
Then make the basis of disaster prevention
然後做防災的基礎
So here at the Zhongyingyuan
所以在中營院這邊
In fact, it has always played a very important role
事實上一直都扮演很重要的角色
This is from Teacher Liang Wenzhong
這是梁文忠老師的
We are on the official website of the Earth Institute of the Zhongying Institute
我們在中營院的地球所的官網裡面
Show it directly and GPS ground deformation
直接就秀出來還有GPS大地變形
That is, except for the situation that happened during the earthquake
就是我除了地震的時候發生的狀況之外
I still need to know
我還要知道
Entire plate collides with Taiwan
整個板塊碰撞到台灣
how is it
它是怎麼樣
how energy is accumulated
能量是怎樣累積的
how much it accumulated
它累積了多少
how fast it accumulates
累積了多快
that of course is back to us
那當然就是回到我們
It was later shown with the so-called seismic hazard
後來用所謂的地震危害顯示
such a job
這樣的工作
Then this is actually for Backbone
那這個事實上就是給Backbone
Just one he must be stable
就是一個他一定要穩定
and he can't disconnect
而且他不能斷線
And permanently maintain the highest quality signal
而且永久的保持最高品質的訊號
Then this quality control
那這個 quality control
Of course the most important thing
當然是最重要的一件事情
that besides this
那除了這個之外
Many developments in the past twenty or thirty years
在二三十年來的很多發展
Although I just talked about the generation of light
雖然我剛剛講說光世代
It's not that we were twenty or thirty years ago
不是說我們二三十年前
didn't do anything
都沒有做什麼事情
but twenty or thirty years ago
而是在二三十年前
we have started to develop
我們已經開始發展
the entire earthquake signal
把整個的地震訊號
Hope to prevent disasters from earthquakes
希望以地震防災
Just mentioned by the vice president
剛剛副院長提到的
A very important role in our earthquake science is
我們地震科學很重要的角色是
give back to society
回饋到社會上面
when an earthquake occurs
地震一發生的時候
how the hell do we get
我們到底如何得到
what is the fastest message
最快的訊息是什麼
So this is a solemn admission
所以這是莊嚴就院
the same is within us
一樣就是我們所內的
Dr. Li Xianzhong received
李憲中博士得到
is our signal
就是我們訊號
the signal just said
剛剛講的訊號
In fact I am every second
事實上我是每秒鐘
Actually every 0.01 seconds
事實上是每個0.01秒
The signal keeps coming in
訊號就一直傳進來
So let's build
所以呢我們先建立好
Database of Seismic Waves of All Taiwan
全台灣地震波的資料庫
Then as long as the earthquake comes every two seconds
那只要地震一來每兩秒
In fact, whether there is an earthquake or not
其實不管有沒有地震
Every two seconds I react by myself
每兩秒我就自己去做反應
Going to explain my current vibration
去了解說我現在的震動
Is it an earthquake
是不是地震
Therefore, we can quickly
所以呢我們可以最快速的在
two seconds or even ten seconds
兩秒甚至十秒
we can book the earthquake
我們就可以訂出地震的
size
規模大小
and its location
還有它的位置
that this is now
那這個是現在
There are many collaborations with the weather track list
跟氣象曲單有很多合作
or everyone here
或者是在座的各位
may work for us
可能對我們的工作
some familiar words
有些熟悉的話
That's when we have an earthquake every time
就是我們每次地震一發生的時候
We will directly poss up
我們就直接poss上去
Many friends also directly
那很多朋友也是直接
just look online
就上網去看
I see a lot of friends on Facebook
我看Facebook很多朋友
So directly put this network
所以直接就把這個網
As far as the post is concerned, where is the earthquake?
就Post上來說這個地震在哪裡
For example, this is the Hualien earthquake on February 6, 2018
例如說這是2018年2月6號的花蓮地震
At this moment, of course we can put
那這瞬間我們當然就可以把
size, depth
規模大小、深度
Solve for its positive element mechanism
為它的正元機制解
All solved and its maximum position
全部都解出來還有它的最大位置
That's totally intelligent
那這個完全都是智慧性的
It is completely Online
就是完全是Online
Then Real Time directly and automatically
然後Real Time直接自動的
do the program work
做這個方案的工作
Then this is one of the very important contributions
那這個是其中一個非常重要的貢獻
It is just mentioned in the past 10 years
就是過去10年在剛剛提到的
Taiwan Earthquake Science Center
台灣地震科學中心
important work done
所做的很重要的工作
outside of scientific research
在科學研究之外
How to really feedback the information of the whole Society
如何真正feedback到整個Society的訊息
Well, this is of course another important task.
那這個是當然另外重要的工作
is also in
就是也是在
It will be seen in the official website of the Earth Institute
地球所的官網裡面會看到的
every time an earthquake occurs
每次地震發生的時候
There will be more than 600 steps in Taiwan
就會有全台在600多步站
We get Real Time's Share Map anytime
我們隨時就得到Real Time的Share Map
the vibration chart
那這個振動的圖表
In fact, earthquake disaster prevention is very important
事實上在地震防災非常的重要
say it's a beauty earthquake
例如說這是美容地震
Maybe everyone is in the middle of the night and it's New Year's Eve
可能大家都在半夜又是大年夜
so no one knows what's going on
所以沒有人知道發生什麼事情
But if you come directly to this page
但是你直接到這個網頁上來的話
You can see that I am in Kaohsiung Tainan
你可以看到說我在高雄台南
Vibrations with a magnitude of 7 or higher are generated near here
這附近產生震度七以上的震動
That's because our earthquake blood is researching
那因為我們地震血在研究
We know this is bound to produce disaster
我們知道這個一定會產生災害
At the beginning, it was also NCDR who directly contacted and said
那當初也是NCDR那邊就直接聯繫說
kink
知道這樣子的凸結
it will surely produce disaster
它一定會產生災害
Then make direct contact with other units of the fire department
那馬上跟消防單位其他單位做直接的聯繫
Then this part is also the shake map of real time every five seconds
那這部分也是每五秒就 real time的 shake map
That's because our Central Plains Institute is currently
那因為我們中原院目前
There are many things that need to be strengthened in terms of law and order
治安的東西有很多很多要加強的地方
So we are currently offline
所以我們目前是 offline
Because of the maintenance of the security firewall
因為治安的防火牆的維護
That's another challenge
那這個就是也是另外一個挑戰
That is, I want to open data
就是我要open data
But I also need a very good firewall
但是我同時要有非常好的防火牆
it's a bit of a dilemma
這有點兩難
but we want to find the balance
但是我們希望找出平衡點
Then this is all open to all people can use
那這個是全部開放給全部的人都可以使用
of course i now
那我當然現在
I know Teacher Liang just met him
我知道梁老師剛碰到他
Said he would come too
說他也會過來
we now hope
我們現在希望
I can play this real time intensity directly to
我可以把這個 real time 的 intensity 直接播放到
above the person's position
所在的人的位置上面
If you put it in the corner where you are
如果你一氣放在你所在的角落的話
That's what we want to develop now
那這是我們目前想要發展一些
work related to communication
跟通訊有關的一些工作
Then this is actually
那這個事實上就是
What we have done over the years
我們在這幾年所做的工作
Of course, these jobs have already played a certain role.
那這些工作其實當然已經扮演一定的角色
Especially since everyone has become familiar with
尤其是大家已經開始熟悉知道
what early warning message
什麼 early warning 的訊息
some people will mention
有些人會提到說
is he borderline
他是不是邊緣人
why didn't he receive
為什麼他沒收到
why did he receive blah blah blah
為什麼他收到等等之類的
Of course if you want to be accurate
那當然如果你要夠準
It must be very high resolution
那一定要非常高的解析度
Because everyone has heard that I am in Shichenglou
因為大家很聽到說我在石城樓
You said the vibration level is 2
你說震度是2
I can't, I'm shaking too much
我不行啊我搖得很大
OK because Shicheng Tower has different
OK 因為石城樓有不同的
different shake sizes
不同的搖晃的大小
There is someone in the Taipei Basin who has been shaking for a long time
那有人在台北盆地他搖得比較久
Some people shake it better on the side of the mountain
有些人在山邊他搖得比較
not so long
比較沒那麼久
But with the current earthquake stations in Taiwan
但是以全台灣現在的地震站
Probably more than 10 kilometers as a resolution
大概是10公里以上當做一個解析度
Well, that's still important in this part.
好 那在這個部分還是很重要
We must say that this most basic backbone
我們必須說這個最基本的backbone
is to keep all signals stable
是維持所有訊號穩定的
important key observation network
重要的關鍵觀測網
then it can instantly locate the scale mechanism
那它可以即時定位規模機制
That probably means we have meteorological laws when we go to Taiwan.
那大概以我們到台灣有氣象法
basically we can't announce the location of the earthquake
基本上我們是不能宣布地震所在的位置
We want the weather bureau to announce
我們是要氣象局宣布的
then what we do is meteorology
那我們所做的工作是氣象
But we are after this real time Maping
但我們在這個real time的Maping之後
There is some interaction with the Meteorological Bureau
跟氣象局是有一些interaction
So but sometimes you'll see that the scale is a little bit different
所以但是有時候你會看到說規模有些不同
the location is a bit different
位置有些不同
That is we probably every earthquake is like last time
那就是我們大概是每次地震像上次的
Ikegami Earthquake
池上地震
September's Ikegami Earthquake
9月的池上地震
a week later
一個禮拜之後
We'll have a joint seminar with the Bureau of Meteorology
我們就會跟氣象局開一個聯合的研討會
Discuss all communication and
討論所有的資訊的傳達跟
Understanding and analyzing data, etc.
跟資料的瞭解分析等等
Well, that's actually going to really see some
好 那事實上真正要看到一些
More precise slices
更精準的斷層
For example, the structure of the Taipei Flat just mentioned
例如剛剛提到的台北平地的構造
you are next to the fault
你是在斷層的旁邊
on the hanging wall of the fault you are on the foot wall of the fault
在斷層的上盤 你在斷層的下盤
etc
等等之類的
You need a lot of more detailed data analysis
你需要很多更細的資料分析
that in the past few years
那在過去幾年以來
In fact, it is just a Geofone Array
事實上就是一個就Geofone Array
That is, you will, we will go out into the field to set up a few side stations
就是你會我們會到野外去擺幾個側站
Which station may be how to go is about a kilometer away
那個側站可能是正樣去大概差一公里
but you need it to have battery impact
但你需要它有電池的影響
It may be operable for about a month, three months
它可能可以operate大概一個月 三個月
but you will do it with your needs
但是你會用你的需要去做這件事情
Well, this actually did a lot
那這個事實上也是做了很多
Especially now that there was a geothermal seminar yesterday
尤其是現在在昨天有個地熱研討會
You mentioned a lot of this kind of Geofone
大家提到很多這種用Geofone
To probe the entire structure in high resolution
去高解析度的探測整個的構造
OK, but while this high-resolution detection
好 但是在這個高解析度的探測的同時
There's something new, and it's called fiber optics.
新的東西出現了 就是所謂的光纖
In fact, everyone is using this optical fiber now.
那這個光纖事實上大家現在已經都在用了
It is Chunghwa Telecom, you will see 5G optical fiber
就是中華電信 你會看到5G的光纖
you have a cable
你有一個Cable
The current practice is to say
那這個現在的做法是說
how do i bury us in the ground
我如何把我們埋在地上的這些
Chunghwa Telecom these cables
中華電信這些電纜
It becomes the observation of the earthquake chair
變成地震椅的觀測
Then its main job is to say
那它最主要的工作是說
I'm next to all the fibers
我在所有的光纖的旁邊
Adding a DARS here is a
這邊加一個DARS 是一個
that is
就是
Distributed Acoustic Sensing
Distributed Acoustic Sensing
it actually shoots a laser beam out
它實際上是打一個雷射光出去
Then if you talk about disturbance
那如果你說到擾動的話
When the laser beam returns
那雷射光回傳的時候
you will have a phase change
你就會產生相位的變化
Phase change from
從相位的變化
I can figure it out and say
我就可以去算出說
How much does it disturb
它到底擾動了多少
how much disturbance
那擾動了多少的時候
Of course I can decide
我當然就可以定出
Where did this disturbance come from?
這個擾動是有哪邊造成的
the fiber optic
那這個光纖的
Monitoring Of course it's not just
監測當然它不是只是
do earthquake
做地震
car waves weather water
車子 海浪 氣象 水
all can
全部都可以
Well, I'm just more focused today.
那我今天只是比較重點式的
to mention its relationship to earthquakes
去提到它跟地震的關係
That's my current job
那以現在的工作
already like i last week
已經像我上禮拜
Three months in Caltic in the United States
三個月在美國Caltic那邊的
work i know has done froding
工作我知道有做Froding
It's now
就是現在
America is now flooding
美國現在在淹水
flooded quite seriously
淹的蠻嚴重的
It's about this aspect of Froding
就是做Froding的這個方面的
natural test is
自然測都是
is allowed
是可以的
of course this part
那當然這一部分
We still have many challenges
大家還是有很多挑戰
I'm buried in the ground
就是我埋在地下
Then all disturbances will be sent
那所有的擾動都會寄過來
So how do I tell if it's a signal
所以呢我如何分辨它是不是訊號
still an earthquake
還是地震
That requires a lot of data analysis of big data
那就需要很多大數據的資料分析
so i will say
所以呢我才會說
I am honored that in my senior years
我很榮幸的在我比較資深的年代
Senior this experience when
資深的這個經驗的時候
to another generation
又跨到另外一個世代
Of course, this is even more interdisciplinary.
那這個當然就更是跨領域的
it's not earthquake blood
它不是地震血而已
It also includes the training of the AI
它還包括AI的訓練
Training materials for Machine Learning
Machine Learning的訓練資料
Because its data is a few terabytes a day
因為它資料是一天這幾個terabytes
how about the whole data
那整個資料怎麼樣
make it fast and accurate
讓它快速又準確
that's another challenge
那這是另外一個挑戰
that job of course
那這個工作當然
Just mentioned I've been thinking about saying
剛剛提到我一直在思考說
Is it possible to do this
做這件事情到底是可以
Advancing our earthquake science
增進我們地震科學
to what extent
導到什麼樣的地步
Actually, I've been thinking about it
其實我一直還在思考這件事情
That is, I can increase the resolution to a higher
就是我可以把解析度提到更高
So how can I parse
那我到底能夠解析
Problems in Earthquake Physics
地震物理的問題
to what extent
解析到什麼樣的程度
this is my thinking
這是我的思考
But in terms of structure, it is absolutely possible to have higher-resolution structural analysis
但在構造上面是絕對可以有更高解析度的構造分析
Can it improve the accuracy of our earthquake early warning?
它是不是可以提升我們地震預警的準確度
Accuracy of Earthquakes
地震動的準確度
For example, if you have a shock level of 2 and a shock level of 3
譬如說你震度2跟震度3
Can I get the correct data more accurately?
我是不是可以更精準的得到正確的數據
That's not to mention looking at energy
那更不用說在能源探看
Because I just saw colleagues from Taipower come over
因為我剛才看到台電的同仁有過來
or some of the other ex-friends
或是其他中有的一些以前的朋友們
Now we are talking about carbon dioxide storage in Taiwan
就是現在在講台灣的二氧化碳封存
Green energy and so on
綠能等等這些問題
So if I pump carbon dioxide into the ground today
那我今天如果把二氧化碳灌到地底下
how carbon dioxide travels
二氧化碳是怎麼走的
We can also map it out
我們一樣都可以把它Maping出來
because I can put all the signals
因為我可以把所有的訊號
All perturbations down to a few micro and even down to a Nano
所有的擾動到幾個micro甚至到Nano
can detect it
都可以把它偵測出來
Everyone, see where my Fiber is placed
大家看我的Fiber到底是擺在哪裡
That's now geothermal carbon sequestration
那就是現在地熱的碳封存
Or if you have questions about geothermal energy
或者是說如果大家有知道一些地熱能量的問題
geothermal exploration
地熱探看
For example in Finland
例如說在芬蘭
Or another earthquake in the Netherlands because of geothermal carbon deposits
或者是在荷蘭因為地熱碳堪又發地震
So shut down the whole factory
所以就把整個工廠 shut down
Is there a way for us to come up with some solutions for this part?
那這部分我們是不是也有辦法提出一些 solution
So it can be applied in a wide range of
所以它可以應用的方面很廣
Then I just talk about it today as the beginning of an era of light
那我今天只是講說它是一個光世代的開始
I must say the whole thing I'm going to share today
我必須說我今天整個要分享的內容
In fact, the future may be even more exciting
其實未來可能更精彩
Today is just a bit of a kick off feeling
今天只是先有點是 kick off 的感覺
Well, the application of this is of course
好 那這個的應用當然
why so accurate
為什麼要到這麼準
we generally speaking
我們一般來講
Of course when the earthquake comes
當然是地震來的時候
you want to shake
你想要搖一搖
know how much i shake
知道說我的搖晃有多少
But our real challenge is to say
但是我們真正的挑戰是說
the beginning of the earthquake
地震一開始
when the first person starts shaking
第一個人開始搖的時候
Do you know if it will be a scale seven or a scale eight
你知道它會成為規模七還是規模八嗎
or do you think it's only scale five
還是你認為它只有規模五
Yes, we are usually when the earthquake hits
對 我們通常都是地震一來的時候
whether you were warned
不管你們受到預警
You must feel it first
你一定先感受一下
How big is my earthquake?
我這個地震它到底搖多大
when you really get nervous
你真的開始緊張的時候
it just stopped
它就停了 還好
but can we do it
但是我們有沒有辦法
Do we have scientifically
我們科學上是不是有
This ability even physically understands
這個能力甚至物理上去理解說
Is there a way to know the beginning of an earthquake?
地震的一開始是不是有辦法知道
How big will it become? Is it possible?
它規模變成多大 到底可不可能
Well, of course, this raises a lot of scientific issues.
那這個當然提到很多科學的問題
But in general industry
可是以一般的產業界來講
The industry began to make a lot of contact with us
產業界開始跟我們做很多接觸
He will tell me, Mr. Mao, I am not doing earthquake prediction.
他會跟我說 毛老師我沒有要做地震預測
but can you tell me how long this earthquake will shake
但是你可以告訴我這個地震要搖多久嗎
Or can I make my machine
或者是我可以讓我的機器
Such as the semiconductor process
像說半導體這些製程
I know when my machine shakes to 20G
我知道我的機器它搖到20G的時候
it may contaminate can i let it be mentioned
它可能會污染 那我可以讓它提嗎
It takes 3 seconds when I mention it takes 2 seconds
我提的時候需要3秒 需要2秒
can i do it
我有辦法做到嗎
So with this kind of dialogue, I actually feel that
那以這樣的對話 其實我就覺得說
very important conversation let me think
很重要的對話 讓我去思考說
what can i do
我到底能做到什麼樣的地步
Then this part of the information becomes very important
那這個部分的資料就變得非常重要
For example, when this signal comes in
例如說這一個訊號進來的時候
when this signal comes in
這個訊號進來的時候
I just mentioned my little signal from the beginning
我剛剛提到 我一開始的小小的訊號
you haven't you probably haven't felt yet
你還沒有 你人可能還沒有感受到
But suppose I
但是假設我
has a very sharp fiber optic
有一個非常敏銳的光纖
even very close side stand
甚至非常近的側站
I can tell it's already a signal
我可以知道它已經是一個訊號了
Then I know that from this signal
那我知道我從這個訊號裡面
can know this signal
可以知道這個訊號
It arrives at the maximum acceleration value
它到後來到最大的加速度值
Does it have a certain regression relationship?
它到底是不是有一定的回歸的關係
How many seconds will it take me to be sure?
那我到底要幾秒的時間才辦法確定說
Will this earthquake cause disaster?
這個地震到底會不會產生災害
I may have no way of knowing where the earthquake is right away
我可能沒有辦法馬上知道地震在哪裡
Because earthquake location takes time
因為地震定位需要時間
You have to have at least three stations to receive
你至少要有三個站以上收到
that's earthquake scale
那但是地震規模
You may not be so accurate right away.
你也不見得馬上就那麼準就定出來
But I know when I shake to a certain degree
但是我當我知道搖到某個程度的時候
For example, our human feelings
例如說我們人的感受
I think everyone in Taiwan must have felt an earthquake
我想在台灣一定都感受過地震
When you shake for more than 10 seconds
當你搖了10秒以上的時候
you will start to get nervous
你會開始緊張了
Do you think that this earthquake will
你會覺得說這個地震是不是會
I should protect myself
我應該要保護一下我自己
Is there even a disaster
甚至是不是有災害
Then our seismology
那我們地震學上面
about 3 seconds
大概就是3秒
That is what we tell us from our empirical data
就是我們從我們的經驗數據裡面告訴我們說
3 seconds before the earthquake signal comes in
地震訊號進來的前3秒
It can tell us it's about to turn into a catastrophic earthquake
它可以告訴我們它會即將變成災害性地震
or not a catastrophic earthquake
還是不會是災害性地震
That is to say, after it comes up in 3 seconds,
也就是說它3秒上來之後
it may go down
它可能就下去了
After 3 seconds it keeps going
3秒之後它繼續走
If you continue walking after 3 seconds
3秒之後繼續走的話
it can produce disaster
它可能產生災害
Although I don't know if it's scale 7 or scale 8
雖然我不知道它是規模7還是規模8
but it will have disasters
但是它會有災害
So I gave a warning
所以我就給預警了
These are some related concepts of earthquake early warning
這是現在地震預警的一些相關的概念
Of course, in terms of decision-making
那當然以決策端來講
It's whether I can be in that moment
它就是我是不是可以在那個瞬間
just make a decision
就做決策
Of course, this decision must be an intelligent one.
那當然這決策一定是智慧性的決策
So this is a high-resolution signal
所以這個就是高解析度的訊號
its important precision
它很重要的精準度
That's why I was referring to the fiber optic
那也是我在提到說這個光纖
Can we make this more precise
是不是可以讓我們在這方面做得更精準
Because we don't want to have Force Alarm either
因為我們也不想有Force Alarm
In general industry
以一般的產業界來講
Force Alarm it also loses a lot
Force Alarm它的損失也很大
so they have to say
所以他們必須說
I need to know my Early Warning
我要知道我的Early Warning
But I'm not a Force Alarm
但是我並不是一個Force Alarm
Otherwise, my Impact would be huge
不然的話我的Impact是很大的
So that's the whole challenge in this place
所以這是整個的挑戰在這個地方
Of course, this is an industrial application
那當然這是產業上的應用
It's about earthquake science.
就是地震科學上面
Great connection with the social body of the whole society
跟整個社會的社會體很大連結
Of course it also mentioned Taiwan
那當然也提到說台灣
I think the news is familiar
我想新聞都很熟悉
Taiwan's semiconductor
就是台灣的半導體
is important to us
是我們很重要的
very important economic value
很重要的這個經濟價值
Then Taiwan is a place with multiple arrays
那台灣又是多陣的地方
then many people will want to say
那很多人就會想說
Then I may have a lot of losses
那這樣子我可能會有很多的損失
Then I also thought
那我同時也是思考說
This is the situation facing Taiwan
這是台灣面對的狀況
So what angle does our science use?
那我們的科學是用什麼樣的角度
can be impacted in this area when
可以在這方面的衝擊的時候
keep us
保住我們本身
won't be affected too much
不會受到太大的影響
At the same time, it has also become a business opportunity for us
同時也變成是我們的商機
It is now that the whole world is developing
就是現在全世界都在發展
In 2010, of course, Japan is doing a lot
2010年其實當然日本在做很多
California is doing it too
加州也在做
Italy and other countries are doing
義大利等等國家都在做
But we have the most earthquake signals
但是我們地震訊號是最多的
that's because you want to train
那因為你要訓練
You need a lot of data
你需要很大筆的資料
Then Taiwan is a large amount of information
那台灣就是大筆資料
important database
重要的資料庫
That's another
那另外是
If the earthquake is far away from me
我如果地震離我人很遠
That Early Warning is useless
那個Early Warning也沒什麼用了
That is to say, five or six years ago
就是說在五六年前
But mainland China is developing a lot Early Warning
但中國大陸在發展很多Early Warning
Then the news mentioned that
然後那時候新聞提到說
Earthquake warnings in Taiwan are poor
台灣的地震預警都很差
Only three seconds, five seconds
只有三秒、五秒
Look at the earthquake in Sichuan in Japan
你看日本那個四川那個地震
It can warn earthquakes for 20 to 30 seconds
它可以地震預警到二十秒到三十秒
In fact, there is a concept to know
其實有概念而知道
Twenty seconds, thirty seconds means the earthquake is very, very far away from you
二十秒、三十秒代表地震離你非常非常的遠
Giving you an Early Warning is actually useless
給你Early Warning其實也沒什麼用
Because I can't say it's useless
因為不能說沒什麼用啦
It should mean that it does not actually cause disasters
應該是說它事實上也不會造成災害
so sometimes we talk
所以有時候我們會講說
Early Warning sometimes becomes Entertainment
Early Warning有時候變成是Entertainment
That's the earthquake warning
就是地震預警受到說
Huh? Did you get it?
欸?你有收到嗎?
Huh? Why didn't I get it? Why didn't you get it?
欸?我為什麼沒收到?你為什麼沒收到?
In fact the whole real purpose is to reduce the shock
事實上整個的真正的目的是要減少衝擊
But sometimes there's this aspect
但是有時候會有這方面
become everyone comparing me
變成大家在比較說我如何
under what conditions
在什麼條件之下收到
Of course, this is something we have discussed a lot with the Qiathlon Bureau and the NCD.
那當然這個是我們跟七項局還有NCD那邊有很多討論啦
That is, we must all test
就是我們一定大家要測試
Everyone can receive this message accurately
大家可以準確的收到這個訊息
Okay back to the science question
好回到科學的問題
There are many important scientific challenges
有很多重要的科學挑戰
that is
就是說
i hope what we do
我希望我們所做的東西
except for the folk
除了對民間
Beyond contributions that are important to our country
對我們國家很重要的貢獻之外
Taiwan's role in earthquake science
我們台灣的角色在地震科學上面
What kind of leadership can there be in the world
在世界上可以有什麼樣領導的
scientific value
科學價值
that just mentioned
那剛剛提到
Everyone is most concerned about earthquake prediction
大家最關心就是地震預測
as long as i say i am a seismologist
只要我講說我是地震學
Including customs clearance to the United States
包括去美國通關
As long as I say I'm a Sesemologist
只要我說我是Sesemologist
He immediately asked me if I could do earthquake prediction
他馬上跟我說我是不是可以做地震預測
Earthquake prediction is a matter of concern to everyone.
那地震預測是大家都關心的問題
Is it possible that he
那他到底可不可能
I just mentioned the earthquake
我剛提到說地震
he was at the beginning
他在一開始的時候
Do you know how big he has become?
你就知道他規模變成多大嗎
How exactly did the earthquake start?
地震到底是怎麼開始的
how did he end
他要是怎麼結束的
In fact, there is still no answer
其實目前為止還是沒有答案
then i keep saying
那我一直在提到說
If you don't know how an earthquake starts
如果你不知道地震如何開始
don't know how he ended
也不知道他如何結束
You can't do earthquake prediction at all
你根本沒有辦法做地震預測
Earthquake predictions just stay in statistics
地震預測只是留在統計
statistics it has a certain value
統計它有一定它的價值
the industry I just mentioned
我剛提到的產業界
they want to know
他們想要知道
earthquake forecasting
地震的 forecasting
how is the estimate
預估是如何
Then we have a certain theory
那我們在一定的學理
can do this work
可以去做這方面的工作
But earthquake prediction works
但地震預測這個工作
He still has many challenges
他還在很多的挑戰
I even often say
那我甚至常常會講說
If the earthquake prediction is successful
如果地震預測成功了
Earthquakes will still come
地震還是會來
Not that you predict earthquakes
不是說你預測地震
Earthquakes don't come, right?
地震就不會來 對嗎
so you really do work
所以你真正要做工作
In fact, earthquake disaster prevention
事實上是地震防災
and earthquake warning
還有地震預警
even
甚至呢
If Earthquake Prediction Fails
地震預測如果失敗的話
the disaster he caused
他所造成的災害
Possibly worse than a real earthquake disaster
可能比真正地震災害還要嚴重
Right, you can think about it
對不對 各位可以想一下
If I talk about a
我今天如果講了一個
Taiwan may be within a week
台灣可能在一個禮拜之內
A scale period of earthquakes
一個規模期的地震
Stocks may plummet
可能股票大跌
everyone wants to go abroad
大家都要出國
or where are you going
或是你到底要跑到哪裡去
last time there was a tsunami
上次有一次海嘯
The first tsunami alarm
第一次的海嘯的alarm
As a result, there was a traffic jam on the highway.
結果高速公路上都塞車了
that this is actually
那這個事實上是
When we're working on this
我們在做這方面工作的時候
how are we getting ready
我們的準備工作到如何
Then I often used to talk to students
那我常常以前會跟學生在講說
my dream but my dream i don't think i can make it
我的夢 但是我的夢 我覺得我不可能達成
That's me, if the earthquake prediction is successful
就是我如果可以地震預測成功
Then make it a hundred times the energy into a real energy that can be used
然後把它能量 百倍成 真正可以應用的能量
I think earthquake prediction is feasible
我才會覺得地震預測才是可以可行的
or worth doing
或者是說值得去做的
Otherwise the work we do
那不然的話 我們所做的工作
Earthquake early warning and earthquake disaster prevention
就是地震預警跟地震防災
How do we proceed with earthquake early warning and earthquake disaster prevention?
那地震預警跟地震防災 我們怎麼進行是怎樣
For example, how do I put Taiwan but the whole world is the same
例如說我如何把台灣 但全世界都一樣
The location of these fault zones that may produce earthquakes in Taiwan
把台灣可能產生地震這些斷層帶的位置
not very clear
沒平得非常的清楚
This is what we do with geologists
這是我們跟地質學家一起在合作的工作
However, the Geological Survey Institute, the Meteorological Bureau, and many related units
但地調所 氣象局 很多相關的單位
how do i know where the fault is
我如何知道斷層在哪裡
When will this fault move?
那這個斷層什麼時候會動
how much does it move
它一動會動多少
If it moves, what about the mayor of Taipei?
它如果動的時候 台北市長怎樣
what will happen
會有怎麼樣的狀況
what will happen to my family
我家會怎麼樣的狀況
the location of a place how it will be
某個地方的位置它會是怎樣的狀況
That's what we're talking about now
那這是我們現在跟
National Disaster Prevention Science and Technology Center
就是國家災害防災科技中心
Or something that the Ministry of the Interior Interdepartmental Council is doing
或者是內政部跨部會在執行的工作
It is a drill for a large-scale earthquake every September
就是每年9月份為一個大規模地震的演練
But this part is not precise enough
但這部分還不夠精準
That's how I know about earthquake fault systems
就是我如何知道地震斷層系統
For example, the Chishang earthquake on September 18
例如說9月18號池上地震
It moves both faults
它兩個斷層都動了
Central Sanpai fault to the west
中央三派斷層往西
Chishang Fault to the east
池上斷層往東
both moved
兩個都動了
The 1906 Meishan Earthquake
1906年的梅山地震
It actually you see an east-west Meishan fault
它事實上你看到一個東西向的梅山斷層
But in fact its real motion structure
但是事實上它真正的運動構造
is the movement structure underneath
是在底下的運動構造
Then the reverse fault becomes a strike fault
然後逆斷層變成走向斷層
Is there a way for us to do these things first?
這些行為我們是不是有辦法先
understand its shape
把它的形貌了解出來
even academically
甚至歷學上面
If my fault jumps to another fault
我這個斷層如果跳到另外一個斷層
Or the 1935 Hsinchu-Taichung Earthquake
或者是1935年的新竹台中地震
It is an earthquake with a greater disaster than 921
它是比921還要更大災害的地震
It is actually three faults
它事實上是三個斷層
From reverse faults to dead faults to strike faults
從逆斷層到亡斷層到走向斷層
How are these mechanisms formed?
這些機制到底是怎麼樣形成的
so real earthquake science
所以真正的地震科學
I don't think it's just about earthquake prediction
我認為不是只是地震預測這件事情
real science is understanding
真正的科學在理解
How did the fault break
斷層是怎麼破
Is there a way for me to know the shape of the fault in advance?
我是不是有辦法事先瞭解斷層的形貌
how to count
怎麼樣計成
And what happens to him when he moves?
還有他如果動的時候他會怎樣呢
We are now finding more and more into fault vibrations
我們現在越來越發現進斷層振動
You fault away from your location
你斷層離你的位置
when you fault
你斷層進的時候
a very long period signal
一個非常長周期的訊號
The stunned shout he produced will be introduced later
他產生的呆喊等一下會有些介紹
then again
那再來的話就是
How do I know which fault he's moving when
我如何瞭解哪個斷層他在動的時候
Can I simulate it first?
我可不可以事先先模擬出來
that this morning
那今天早上
I'm actually at noon today
今天中午事實上我在
National Disaster Prevention Science Center
國家災害防救科學中心
we are talking
我們在講說
What we now call digital chaos
我們現在所謂的數位亂生
Digital Twin
Digital Twin
How do I take my Synaryl
我如何把我的Synaryl
become a VR
變成一個VR
Then I can have a solution
然後我可以有一個solution
is coming in
是進來的
that part too
那這部分也是
digital transformation
以現在所謂的數位轉型
Or in the current big data data
或是現在的大數據的資料裡面
work that can be contributed
都可以貢獻的工作
Then accurately predict the earthquake
然後準確的預估出地震動
That certainly doesn't sound like it has anything to do with the light.
那當然聽起來好像跟光線沒什麼關係
the fact that light i mentioned
那事實上光線我提到
it actually increases the resolution
它事實上是提高解析度
let me all countries on this side
讓我這方面所有國家
Make a more accurate observation component
做更精準的一個觀測的component
Okay, so if the answer to an earthquake is a more scientific question
好 那地震如果回答說比較科學的問題
That's how the earthquake started
就是地震到底是怎麼開始的
How do I know the earthquake from the first 0.01 seconds
我如何知道地震從一開始的0.01秒
When it starts to bite, how big is it?
開始咬的時候 它到底是咬多大
Earthquake it's a random act
地震它是一個隨機的行為
or is it a self-similarity act
還是是一個自我相似性的行為
so some people will want to say
所以有些人會想說
Why should I have an earthquake on a scale 2
我為什麼要在一個規模2的地震
I'm even on a scale -1 earthquake
我甚至在一個規模-1的地震
Because I want to know how the earthquake started
因為我要知道地震是怎麼開始的
How did that moment come out?
那個瞬間出來是怎麼樣開始的
There are probably a lot of different theories on this part.
那這個部分大概有很多不同的理論
to explore, for example, that it has self-similarity
去探討 例如說它有自我相似性
or cascadia
或者是cascadia
It actually doesn't know if it will do it
它事實上是不知道自己會不會做到
It changes as it encounters
它是碰到怎樣就變怎樣
What if this is the case?
如果是這樣子的狀況之下呢
It's hard to predict earthquakes
很難做地震預測
Which means my earthquake is actually a random act
也就是說我地震事實上是一個隨機的行為
Of course it's not random
當然它的隨機也不是
It should mean that I did not judge the shape of the entire fault zone
應該是說我要沒評出整個斷層帶的型貌
I don't know its strain value
不知道它的應變值怎樣
Strength and fault give me resistance
力量跟斷層給我的抗拒力量
who is bigger
誰比較大
I can decide whether I want to move forward and continue to break
能夠決定我到底要往前繼續破
still have to stop
還是要停下來
The other way is to say
那另外一種就是說
I Earthquake In fact there is one
我地震事實上是不是有一個
preparatory behavior
準備又發的行為
I am in one place first
就是我在一個地方先
After accumulating energy
累積進能量之後
then start breaking out
然後再開始破出去
Well, this is of course a scientific challenge.
那這個當然就是科學的挑戰
The role of the science challenge
那這科學挑戰的角色
Of course, the previous data were all on the surface.
當然以前的資料都是在地表
or that its data is limited
或者是說它的資料有限
Farther away from the location of the real small earthquake
離真正的小地震的位置比較遠
So there is no way to get it very precisely.
所以沒辦法很精準的得出來
Not only do I hope that the future's glamorous data
我不但希望未來的光鮮的資料
is there a way to work on this
是有辦法在這方面的工作
come up with a higher resolution
提出更高的解析
For example, a few seconds before the beginning
這個例如說一開始前面幾秒
this is one second
這個是一秒
or one to six seconds
或是一到六秒
Earthquakes of different sizes from 6.7 to 8.7
不同規模地震從六點七到八點七
You will find it difficult to judge at the beginning
你會發現它的開始是很難去做判斷的
That is to say, we may very well imagine that
也就是說我們可能很自己的想像說
It may be relatively slow for small-scale earthquakes
小規模地震它可能會比較緩
massive earthquake
大規模地震
In fact, it may be shaking
其實它可能比較抖
no
no
it actually
它事實上
It might be shaking at first for a small earthquake
小規模地震一開始它可能很抖
but it flattened out again
但是它又平下來
OK
OK
so tell us
所以告訴我們說
I want a few seconds from the beginning of the 0.0 signal
我要從一開始的0.0幾秒的訊號
to assess how big the earthquake will be
去評估這個地震會變多大
it is challenging
它是有挑戰的
but where is its real challenge
但它真的挑戰在哪裡呢
Because my stations are all above the surface
因為我這些站都是在地表上面
Above the surface my various noises
在地表上面我各種不同的雜訊
I have a submerged reflection signal
我有潛程的反射訊號
I have this shockwave zoom in on the grade layer
我有成績層的這個震波放大
i have all kinds of pollution
我有各種不同的污染
That's why we keep referring to earthquakes
所以呢我們才會一直把地震
I always hope that the deeper the better
一直希望擺在越深越好
So you will go to the so-called special police
所以就會到所謂的專警到警下
That's what I just mentioned
那這也是我剛提到說
Although such challenges have been encountered in the past
雖然在以前碰到這樣的挑戰
but in theory
但是在理論上面
We know that when 3 seconds
我們知道3秒的時候
My initial signal can tell me
我的一開始的訊號可以告訴我
If I surpass a government like this
我如果超過這樣子的政府的話
can tell me about the earthquake
可以告訴我這個地震
At least scale 6 and above
至少是規模6以上
So I can start giving earthquake warnings
所以呢我可以開始給地震預警
Below 6 we may
6以下我們可能
but limited to the west
但以西向局限的
the regulations say
的法規是說
Positive degree 5 or scale 6 or above
正度五或者是規模六以上
Early warning of earthquakes with a scale of 5.5 or more
規模五點五以上給地震預警
ok that job
好 那這個工作
This work was published in 2005
這個工作發表在2005年
In 2005, the data base behind the important
2005年其實重要的後面的資料基礎
All earthquake data from Taiwan
都是台灣的地震資料
This is Mr. Wu Yimin
這是當初吳亦民老師
the one just mentioned
就是剛剛提到的那個
Initial work on the entire orthographic map of PLR
PLR整個正度圖的一開始的工作
In fact, the whole of Taiwan is used
事實上是使用全台灣
The most dense data about nearly 20 years
最密集大概將近20年的資料
Do the understanding of the whole signal
做整個訊號的理解
To understand the possibility of explaining this earthquake warning
去了解說這個地震預警的可能性
Of course, it goes without saying that in the past ten years
那當然不用說這十年來
Everyone has become more and more familiar
已經大家都已經越來越熟悉了
That concept was actually being talked about ten years ago
那在十年前事實上一直在講這個概念
Of course this concept needs a lot
那當然這個概念有很多需要後
All signals in the latter part
後段所有的訊號
Let all the resources in the latter stage be completed
後段的所有的資源讓它去完成
Of course it's not
那當然它也不是
doused and wet
灌污一濕的
That is to say, when the earthquake warning was issued
也就是說當初在推地震預警的時候
some people have a concept
有些人會有一個概念
but very accurate
但是非常準確的
his concept he mentioned
他的概念 他有提到說
Earthquake warnings are useless
地震預警是沒什麼用的
Because you can give early warning somewhere
因為你可以給預警的地方
He's not that bad anymore
他差害已經不大了
OK because your government has decayed
OK 因為你政府已經衰減了嘛
But he is not necessarily accurate
但是他也不見得是準確
I must say, suppose there is an earthquake today
我必須說 假設今天地震
How many times did the 921 earthquake hit Taipei?
921地震在幾幾台北市上
About 10 seconds 20 seconds warning time
大概有10秒 20秒的預警時間
But Taipei because of its shock wave amplification
但是台北因為他有震波放大
So you have a moderate amount of forewarning.
所以呢 你有適度的預警
But not to mention high-speed rail, MRT
但更不用說高鐵啊 捷運啊
These things are already
這些東西都已經是
directly already in use
直接已經是在使用的
But this concept is not
可是這個概念也是沒有
his concept
他講的概念
It is generally challenging the concept of earthquake early warning
就是一般在挑戰地震預警的概念
nothing wrong
也沒有錯
That is to say, my real challenge is
就是說 我真的挑戰是
I On site Erling Undead
我On site 二陵亡靈
How do I make my blind spot smaller and smaller
我如何讓我的盲區是越來越小的
Which means I'll build an earthquake signal in.
也就是說 我建一個地震訊號進來
I have to have three stations to receive
我必須要三個站才可以收到
So, I passed it through three stations
所以呢 我三個站傳過來
You are at a depth of 10 kilometers
你都深度在10公里
It's already going to cost three stations
三個站傳過來已經要花掉
two or three seconds
兩三秒的時間
Not to mention I also need data processing
更不用說我還要data processing
I want to go out again
我還要再二陵亡靈出去
you want the signal to come in
你要訊號收進來
You throw it out after you get it
得到之後你再丟出去
Then the whole time is delayed
那整個的時間就delay了
So there is a big blind spot
所以就有很大的盲區
That's about 30 kilometers, 50 kilometers
就是大概30公里 50公里
That is to say, if Jingyuan is right next to you
就是說靜遠如果就在你的旁邊
you have no chance of getting
你根本沒有機會拿到
time to get warning
拿到預警的時間
Of course we are developing now
那當然我們現在在發展的
Unsee Aluminium Wondering 4
Unsee Aluminium Wondering 4
Earthquake 10 kilometers deep in the ground
你在地底下10公里深的地震
You may still have 1 2 seconds
你可能還是會有1 2秒
Effective
有效的
But this is not from the weather bureau
但是這個不是氣象局的
Regional Earthquake Early Warning
區域地震預警
Bureau of Meteorology We are now receiving
氣象局我們現在收到的
Earthquake warnings issued by Meteorological Bureau are regional earthquake warnings
氣象局地震預警都是區域地震預警
just after some distance
就是有一段距離之後
you will get an earthquake warning
你會得到地震預警
but you are there
但是你在旁邊
For example, the Ikegami earthquake
例如說池上地震
you are on the pool
你就在池上
You have no chance of getting an earthquake warning signal
你沒有機會拿到地震預警的訊號
because time is too late
因為時間還來不及
Then our real challenge now is
那我們現在真的挑戰就是
How do I future is there a chance to use
我如何未來是不是有機會用
this bright signal
這種光鮮的訊號
I can make the blind spot smaller and smaller
我可以讓盲區越來越小
I can't say with absolute certainty that it's perfectly fine
我沒有辦法絕對說它完全可以
But because the challenge is great
但是因為挑戰很大
like me this morning ourselves
像我今天早上我們自己
Guru Meeting is doing Aluminum Wondering of AI
Guru Meeting在做AI的Aluminium Wondering
just mentioned
就提到說
It seems that after the Chigami earthquake
好像池上地震一發生之後
nearby
旁邊的
Those stations are all disconnected
那幾個站全部都斷線了
So even if my data processing site is good
所以就算我的資料處理的站怎麼好
Well done Fly
Fly都做得很好
Actually the earthquake shook it and it disconnected
實際上地震一搖它斷線了
So we can't do it
所以呢我們也做不來
So I just introduced to you
所以我剛剛跟各位介紹
Real-Time Moment Tensors made by Mr. Li Xiancong
李仙聰老師做到的Real-Time Moment Tensors
So we later have many versions that are
所以我們後來有很多版本就是
Scale 6 scale 5 both work fine
規模6規模5都運行得很好
because it's all online
因為都在線上
A scale of 7 has several stations that may be
規模7有幾個站可能是
Will Centralize or disconnect
會Centralize掉或斷線掉
So we mentioned at that time that I really wanted to challenge
所以呢我們那時候提到說我真的要挑戰是
An earthquake with a magnitude of 8.0 in the Ryukyu Trench is in the open sea
琉球海溝規模8.0的地震在外海
Then we're going to use the Japanese signal
那我們要用到日本的訊號
Signals used in the Philippines
用到菲律賓的訊號
Signals used in Mainland China
用到中國大陸的訊號
to skip Taiwan
要跳開台灣
Then how do we have an instant signal exchange
那我們如何有一個即時的訊號的交換
Then this is also the Earth Institute of the Chinese Academy
那這也是中文院地球所這邊
Cooperate with many international
跟國際上很多合作
That is, I have direct data exchange
就是我有直接的資料的交換
can keep me on our island
可以讓我在我們島內
In the case of a large-scale earthquake and power outages
有大規模地震都斷電的狀況之下
i can still function
我還是可以運作
If you have the opportunity to compare yourself
如果在做有機會比較自身的
will know
會知道
During the 921 earthquake, the COFCO radio station collapsed and nothing was left
921地震的時候中糧電台一倒 什麼都沒了
I remember back then that I still had to talk over the phone
那時候我記得我還必須要透過電話
Let my Japanese friends tell me what happened
讓日本的朋友告訴我到底發生什麼事情
Then as long as there is power, grab the signal and start analyzing it.
那只要有電的時候就趕快把訊號抓回來開始做分析
Of course, the experience of 921 taught our country a lot
那當然那個921的經驗讓我們國家學了很多
So we are now in the Ministry of Science and Technology
所以我們現在就是在在科技部這些
When the National Science and Technology Council does these tasks, it will mention that
國科會這些工作的時候就會提到說
How do I ensure critical infrastructure is not compromised
我如何確保關鍵基礎設施是不會受損的
So the simulation of the large-scale earthquake we just talked about
所以我們在剛剛講的大規模地震的模擬
I want to know where the Taipower tower is
我要知道台電的電塔是在什麼位置
gas it won't it leak because
瓦斯它會不會它會不會漏氣因為
It's just that if there is a leak, it will cause a fire.
就是漏氣的話它會產生火災
Are our facilities complete in this part?
這部分我們的設施是不是都要完備
Here's what we're doing with massive earthquakes
這是我們大規模地震在做的工作
Well, of course, this is very early work.
那這當然是很早前的工作
But I think it's worth watching directly with you
但是我覺得是很值得可以直接跟各位看
For example, during the 921 earthquake
例如說921地震的時候
You can see that the earthquake took ten or twenty seconds
你可以看到這地震發生時間十幾二十秒
Seismic waves began to spread to Taichung
地震波開始傳到台中地方
The government here in Fengyuan is very big
政府豐原這邊政府非常的大
it breaks from south to north
它是由南往北破
So there is a relatively large government in the north
所以北邊產生比較大的政府
You will see that Taipei currently has no
你會看到台北目前其實還沒有
So we have about 40 seconds
所以我們大概有40秒的時間
Early warning to Taipei
可以預警到台北
Of course, this concept is already underway.
那當然這個概念目前已經都在進行了
I just wanna say it's a really good
我只是想說這是一個非常好的
The demo lets you see what the concept of early warning is
demo讓各位看說預警的概念是什麼
Of course I don't now
當然我現在沒有把
I need a signal received
我需要訊號收到
and then send out these times
然後再發出去這些時間
But in fact these are already being resolved
但事實上這些都已經在解決了
Then of course when you arrive in Taipei City
那當然你到台北市的時候呢
Use three-dimensional transmission in this management line
在這支理線中用三維的傳遞
It is very important to calculate this information
算出來非常重要的這些資訊
Of course there are layers of problems in the Taipei Basin
當然台北盆地有成績層
These signals need to be higher and higher resolution
這些訊號要越來越高解析度的話
We can see the seismic waves inside the basin
我們可以看到地震波在盆地裡面
how does it shake and how long does it shake
它是怎麼晃的會搖多久
So you'll talk about when Earthquake Island comes
所以你會講說地震島來的時候
how long did you shake
你到底搖多久
because the longer you shake
因為你搖得越久
Of course there will be some disasters
當然就會有一些災害
How long can I shake it
我是有辦法把搖得多久
This matter is also included in the information
這件事情也放到資訊裡面
This is what I personally consider my second generation seismic domain
這是我個人認為我的第二代地震域
I hope my second-generation earthquake warning is based on the floor level and the degree of shaking
我希望我的第二代地震預警是樓層的還有搖晃程度
It can be included in the concept of earthquake early warning
是可以放到地震預警的概念裡面來
These tasks are actually the basic information behind
那這些工作其實後面的基礎資料
high-resolution basic data
就是高解析度的基礎資料
This is also back to the bright
這也是回到剛講光鮮
At that time, we hoped that several scenes in the Taipei Basin
我們那時候有希望說台北盆地裡面的幾個景
I can also play bright
我也可以放光鮮的時候
I can parse the whole related construct more clearly
我可以把整個的相關的構造解析得更清楚
the whole job of course
那整個的工作當然
this is what i just mentioned
這個就是我剛提到
We started 10 years ago
我們在10年前開始成立
It is the Taiwan earthquake model under the framework of the Taiwan Earthquake Science Center
就是在台灣地震科學中心的架構之下的台灣地震模型
Cross-departmental committees cast all these tasks in
跨部會的把這些工作全部都鑄到進來
For example, the Shanjiao fault that everyone is familiar with in the Taipei Basin
例如說台北盆地大家比較熟悉的山腳斷層
that in order
那依依序的進行
In fact, September of this year is the Xin-Chen Fault, which is on the Hsinchu side.
那今年的9月事實上是新陳斷層就是新竹這邊
So your drill in September is also calculated by us.
所以你們9月份的演練那也是我們算的
That is, the exercise in September will focus on new and old faults
就是9月份的演練會是以新陳斷層為主
Then next year will focus on Chiayi
那明年會是以嘉義為主
That is, we will continue to work with ministries related to the Ministry of the Interior
就是我們會持續的跟內政部相關的部會
to get to know them
去了解他們
requirements on the application
在應用上面的需求
If you want to be accurate
那如果要算得準
That is to say, you are talking about the simulation of seismic waves.
就是說你說地震波的模擬這一部分
Since ten or twenty years ago
從十幾二十年前就已經
very, very many people are developing
非常非常很多人在發展
Then of course we mentioned that
那我們當然那時候提到說
simulation
simulation
It is already difficult to write programs for agents
代理寫程式已經是很難了
After you build someone else's program
等你建入了別人的程式之後
You just enter and then output
你就一個entered然後就一個output
Then let me tell you that you are garbage in garbage out
那然後我講說你是 garbage in garbage out
who knows right
who knows right
So the simulation at that time was actually
所以那時候的 simulation 事實上
It took a lot of effort to convince that
花了很多功夫去convince說
ours is
我們這個是
of scientific value is
科學價值的是
validation came out
validation 出來的
Because of too many different simulations
因為太多不同的 simulation
can come in
可以進來
So we have to be very accurate
所以呢我們必須要非常準確
I know that the data I entered is
知道說我進去的data是
is reliable
是可靠的
We spent a lot of time on that part
那這一部分我們花了很多時間
With earthquake engineering and with national units
跟地震工程跟國家單位
do this communication
做這方面的溝通
So we can take all the criteria
所以呢我們可以把所有的準則
list them all
都列出來
Then I just mentioned the structure of the entire basin
那我剛提到說整個盆地的構造
We still have certain limitations in resolution
我們現在在解析度還是有一定的限制
So my current signal is about 0.5Hz for 2 seconds
所以我現在的訊號大概是0.5Hz 2秒
5 seconds but the real one seems to be 1Hz to 10Hz
5秒 但真正的好像是1Hz到10Hz
Then your resolution must be very high, and the calculation program must be very large.
那你的解析度要非常高 計算的程式要非常大
Then we certainly hope that the future fiber will allow us to do this work
那我們當然希望未來的fiber可以讓我們做這方面的工作
push the structural resolution of my basin to become clearer
把我的盆地的構造解析度推到越來越清楚
The other teacher who just talked about cooperation, Mr. Huang Xinhua
那另外剛剛講的合作的老師 黃信華老師
he is making mountains
他身上在做山峰
When I use optical fiber, is it shaken by an earthquake?
我用光纖是不是地震搖晃的時候
Or when it rains heavily, there will be landslides
或者是下大雨的時候會有土石流
Can I monitor the display of landslides
我是不是可以監測土石流的顯示
That's also supported by the plan of the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine.
那也是中醫院這邊的計畫在支持
we're doing the big death part
我們在做大死的部分
In addition to earthquakes, there are also extended disasters such as landslides.
除了地震之外 還有土石流這種延伸災害的這些工作
For example, there are basin structures but no basin structures
那例如說有盆地構造沒有盆地構造
You can see clearly that this is
你可以看到很清楚這個是
When there is a structure in the Taipei Basin
有台北盆地的構造的時候
You will see the seismic waves when the ship lands
你會看到地震波在船地的時候
He just showed you
他在剛剛已經有給各位看
This is Dr. Constitutionalist's calculation.
這是憲民者博士算的
his resonant behavior in
他在裡面共振的行為
but you will see say
但你會看到說
Because this is a triangle fault
因為這個是三角斷層
which we provided to the Ministry of the Interior
當初我們提供給內政部的
You sometimes mentioned on the news that
你有時候在新聞上面提到說
so-and-so member or whoever mentioned said
某某委員或是誰提到說
If an earthquake with a magnitude of 6.4 occurs in Taipei,
台北如果產生規模6.4的地震的話
How many houses will collapse
會有多少的房子倒啊
how many people were injured
多少人損傷
That's actually what we calculated
那事實上就是我們算的結果
Give it to NCDR to see their entire
交給NCDR去看他們整個的
the structure of the house
的房屋的結構
then start pushing
那開始去推
Internal reinforcement
內政補強
even new building codes
甚至新的建築法規
Then I think these tasks are slowly going on.
那我覺得這些工作是慢慢的在進行
Then you see it's still biting
那你看這邊還在咬
This part is over
這個部分已經是結束了
so this is
所以這是
Fine Velocity Structure
精細的速度構造
allows us to calculate more precisely
可以讓我們算得更精準
so i've been thinking
所以我一直在想說
From 5 to have is relatively simple
從5到有是比較簡單的
but from there to better
但是從有到更好
I think everyone has experience with this challenge
這個挑戰我想大家都有經驗
You can pass the test to 80 points
你從考及格到80分還可以
you score 80 to 90
你80分到90分
Efforts can also be achieved
努力也可能達到
But you're going from 99 to 100
但是你要從99變到100
1 point for this
這個那1分
In fact, it takes a lot of effort
事實上是要很大很大的努力
So now we actually want to go from 80 to 90
那我們現在事實上就是希望從80到90
slowly push forward to better
慢慢往前推到更好
Is there a chance for this signal first?
那光先這個訊號是不是有機會
let's do this
讓我們做這件事情
Of course it goes into the process
那當然進段程
This is the time to enter section 921
這是進段程921的時候
nearby station
靠近的車站
These are protected from wind bridges, shot collapse, and so on.
這些被風橋 防射倒塌等等之類
The most important thing is this very signal from the Cheung Chau flag
最主要就是這個非常長洲旗的訊號
This speed signal is a possible way
這個速度訊號就是一個possible way
A Cheung Chau flag signal
一個長洲旗的訊號
Push the house down
把房子一推就倒了
How did the Cheung Chau flag signal come from?
那這個長洲旗的訊號它是怎麼來的
At that time we published
那時候我們發表
It was our TCTP at that time
就是我們那時候TCTP
We publish in some of the top
我們發表在一些比較頂級的
Journals to discuss
期刊上面去探討
how the hell did it happen
它到底是怎麼發生的
For example, it's actually when an earthquake occurs
例如說它事實上是地震在發生的時候
it can also accelerate
它也可以加速度
a speed
一個速度
But when it reaches its maximum speed
但是它速度達到最大值的時候
My displacement continues to slide forward
我的位移繼續往前滑
Because my section contains
因為我的段程帶裡面
If it is a very detailed
如果是一個非常細密的
If the ring keeps slipping
一直滑的戒指的話
My minerals and time-lapse
我的礦物跟延時
In fact, particles down to the nanometer
事實上可以達到奈米的顆粒
When it comes to nano particles
到奈米的顆粒的時候
I fact many thermodynamic influences
我事實上很多熱力學的影響
my big doubts arise when i have
我的很大的懷疑的時候我產生
smoperturization
smoperturization
After letting my faults open
讓我的斷層拉開了之後
I'll slide forward even bigger
我就往前滑得更大
that this part we are not
那這個部分我們是不是
There is a way for casting
有辦法for casting
is that I can figure out that
就是我可以算出說
if a scale
如果一個規模
When reaching 7.0
達到7.0的時候
behavior like this happens
這樣的行為就是會發生的
Then I for my disaster prevention work
那我對於我的防災的工作
it is very important to understand
就非常重要去瞭解
But science is more important
但科學上面更重要
At that time in 9.1
那時候9.1的時候
Many scholars come to Taiwan
很多學者來台灣
He explored why an earthquake
他探討說為什麼一個地震
can have so much energy
可以有這麼大的能量
Theoretically, the hard force generated by the crust
理論上地殼它產生的硬力
Shouldn't be that hard
不應該有那麼大的硬力
In fact it's all kinetic
事實上這完全是動力學產生的
It is a passive kinetic behavior
它是一個被動式的動力學的行為
of course now
那當然現在的
Dynamics simulation can handle this matter
動力學模擬都可以去處理這件事情
is in the stage of development
是在發展的階段
that kind of signal
那那樣子的訊號
we asked for advice
我們那時候請教說
All scale 6.7 and above
都是規模6.7以上
Like the 921G earthquake version 7.3 and the version 7.2 earthquake
像921G地震7.3 版生地震7.2
The Landes earthquake 7.2 is a large-scale earthquake
Landes地震7.2 都是大規模地震
But everyone should still remember the Meinong earthquake in 2016
但是大家應該都還記憶猶新的2016年的美農地震
Scale 6.4 Same as a Long period of ground motion
規模6.4 一樣一個Long period of ground motion
This Long period of ground motion is no longer a
這個Long period of ground motion再也不是一個
think it may have happened by accident
覺得它可能是不小心發生的
We now feel more and more that it is a physical phenomenon
我們現在越來越覺得它是一個physical的現象
it is a physical phenomenon
它是一個物理的現象
It's just that the seismic instruments were not placed so densely before.
只是以前地震儀器沒有擺得那麼密
so no detection
所以沒有偵測到
That's not to mention whether the future light may have the opportunity to see more
那更不用說未來的光線是不是可以機會看到更多
That's why I say earthquake science is an observational science
所以我才會說地震科學是一個觀測的科學
Had a lot of conversations with everyone in the engineering world
跟工程界大家有很多對話
The engineering world used to tell me back then
工程界那時候常常跟我說
Of course we have an earthquake culture preschool attempt
當然我們有一個地震文化學前試圖
He told me, Mr. Meng, you gave too much shock
他跟我說 盟老師你給的震度太大了
This way you can find a way to make it smaller
這樣子你可以想辦法讓它小一點
Then I thought about how to think about it
然後想說 這怎麼想辦法
This is data, I can't think of a way
這是data 我沒有辦法想辦法
it is data
它是data
But in terms of data, they mean
那但是data來講他們是說
In our previous earthquake engineering, it was
我們以前的地震工程裡面是
More than about magnitude 5
超過大概震度5
my house fell down
我的房子就全倒了
In fact we found
那事實上我們發現
A Taiwan egg with a magnitude of 5 may be a well-built house
震度5台灣蛋可能是房子蓋得很好
That's not all down
那沒有到全倒的地步
So something actually
所以有些東西事實上
I need to do a lot of dialogue and exploration.
要再去做很多對話摸索的
So from the beginning I thought
所以從一開始覺得說
This Cheung Chau writing signal happened by accident
這種長洲寫信號是不小心發生的
Up to now, our building regulations in Taiwan
到現在已經我們台灣的建築法規
New building codes have broken into earthquakes
新的建築法規已經有進斷成地震
These building codes all come in
這些建築法規全部都進來了
It was Cheung Chau who wrote the shock
就是長洲寫震動的
Buildings cannot be built in generations
在斷成代是不能蓋大樓的
if you have a private building
如果你有私有建物的話
You must do a special review
你一定要做特別的審查
In fact, this part is included in the laws and regulations.
這部分事實上都法規都進來
it's my pleasure to have the opportunity
就是我很高興有機會
More conversations with engineering
跟工程更多的對話
Then wait a minute and I can introduce you
那等一下可以跟各位介紹
It is in our MIDASData
就是我們MIDASData裡面
See the phenomenon that Cheung Chau wrote to shake it
看到長洲寫震動它的現象
It is actually a fractured structure
它事實上就是斷成的構造
caused by the phenomenon
造成的現象
Okay, that's what I just said
好 那像剛剛講的
The Chigami Earthquake of September 18
9月18號的池上地震
It was the earthquake three months ago
就是三個月前的地震
four months
四個月了
You may have seen this on the news
那這個大家可能在新聞上都看到
these bridges fell
這些橋倒了
Semi-11 in that domain is down here
那個域裡的Semi-11這邊倒了
It's just like a very Long period of ground motion
它就是一樣一個非常Long period of ground motion
caused this disaster
造成這個災害
But some of the same signals are disconnected
但一樣的有些訊號就斷線了
That's what I mentioned to the weather bureau
這也是我跟氣象局提到說
We want a Resilient Society
我們要一個Resilient Society
But we want Resilient Instrumentation
但是我們要Resilient Instrumentation
How do we make earthquakes come
我們如何讓地震來的時候
My station on the nearest fault won't be disconnected
我最近斷層的測站是不會斷線的
Because many of my research materials need near-fault data
因為我很多研究資料需要近斷層的資料
then this is a challenge
那這個是挑戰
Of course I'm actually in the domain
當然我其實在域裡面
I set up some stations to see its signal
我擺了一些測站去看它的訊號
good
好
Okay, so back to the phenomena we were talking about
好 所以回到我們剛剛講的這些現象的時候
of course i want to say
我當然就想說
Why am I talking to the side of the earth?
我為什麼會跟地球所這邊
Let's mention this key breakthrough plan from the Intermediate People's Court.
就中院這邊提這個關鍵突破計劃
because i know it's risky
因為我知道它有風險的
I will thank the hospital for mentioning that
我會感謝院方有提到說
The essential
關鍵
In fact they understand the risks
事實上他們了解有風險
I don't know if it will work
我不知道會不會成功
but i think it's an opportunity
但是我覺得它是個機會
So I propose to try this
所以呢我就提出這樣嘗試
And at that time, I actually mentioned it to Taipower
而且那時候我事實上跟台電中有都有提到
Carbon dioxide sequesters these things
二氧化碳封存這些東西
But everyone is very conservative about the light
但是大家對於光線這件事情都很保守
Then go back to Academia Sinica personally
那回到中研院我個人
It is an honor to come to Academia Sinica
有這個榮幸到中研院來
I know what we're going to do is a lookahead
我知道我們要做的就是一個前瞻
Lead us to Taiwan to challenge a new
帶領我們台灣挑戰一個新的
The possibility of scientific development
科學發展的可能性
that's nice to have a chance we made it
那很高興有機會我們成功了
So start having a lot of conversations
所以開始有很多對話
i can't say we succeeded
我不能說我們成功
It should be said that we put it in
應該說我們擺進去了
The data research is still in the process of writing
資料的研究還在努力的寫當中
Then this is us
那這個的話就是我們
At least we are technically successful
至少我們在技術上面是成功了
We even have conversations with Chunghwa Telecom
甚至我們跟中華電信也有對話
We have a signal that uses Chunghwa Telecom's dialogue
我們有一段訊號是用中華電信的對話
because the real purpose is
因為真正的目的是
All cables in Taiwan
全台灣的所有的電纜
can become our signal
都可以變成是我們的訊號
and submarine cables
還有海底電纜
But it's a big challenge just take it step by step
但它挑戰很大只是一步一步來
When I mentioned it to the hospital, I said
我跟院方在提的時候說
In addition to these applications
除了本來這些應用之外
Not to mention the Millennium Fault
更不用說米倫斷層
Probably the most active fault in the world
應該是全世界最活躍的斷層
Every 70 years
70年就動一次
And it moves exactly the same
而且動的一模一樣
This was moved in 1951
這是1951年動的
It's exactly the same as in 2016
跟2016年動的是一模一樣
In fact, the Ikegami Fault
其實池上斷層
2022 Ikegami earthquake dynamic position
2022年池上地震動的位置
It is exactly the same as the Yuli fault in 1951
跟1951年的玉璃斷層也是一模一樣
After the earthquake
當初這個地震發生之後
we've been thinking
我們在一直在思考
In 1951, this series of steam-scale earthquakes
1951年這一系列規模汽的地震
happen within two months
在兩個月之內發生
what will its condition be like
它的狀況會是什麼樣子
Seismic activity was high at the time
當初的地震活躍度很高
So at that time, the chairman of the National Science Council
所以那時候國科會主委
At that time, he was the Minister of Science and Technology
那時候是科技部部長
Also hold a meeting with us to understand
也跟我們召開會議去理解
What is the nature of its earthquake
說它的地震的特質是如何
Well, Bai Guangguang once said
好 百光線一來是說
Murren Fault it's already clear
米倫斷層它已經很清楚
It is related to the Ryukyu Trench
它是跟琉球海溝
I just mentioned past life on scale 8.0
我剛剛提到規模8.0的前世
Everyone is on the news sometimes
大家有時候會在新聞上
What century-old politics are you referring to?
提到什麼百年大政
since 1920
因為1920年
A magnitude 8 earthquake
一個規模8的地震
Not to mention its entire fault system is linked together
更不用說它整個斷層系統是連在一起的
If an earthquake warning
如果要做地震預警
It should be said before the earthquake
應該說地震前照的話
it is also possible opportunity
它也是可能的機會
So not to mention I was hoping to make a
所以更不用說我是希望做一個
The biggest experiment is how I put the fiber
最大的嘗試就是我如何把光纖
Because the matter of optical fiber has been talked about for two or three years
因為光纖這件事情已經講了兩三年
In fact, it has been talked about for a long time at home and abroad.
在國內外其實已經講了很久了
It's just that there has been no actual operation
只是一直沒有實際的操作
my seminar abroad
我在國外研討會
Of course the time of COVID caused some trouble
當然COVID的時候造成一些困擾
But when in seminars abroad
但是在國外研討會的時候
listen to me
大家聽我說
郭鳳,you have to talk about optical fiber
郭鳳,you have to talk about optical fiber
I've been thinking that I'm going to smoke this hilarious
我一直在想說我要抽這個熱鬧嗎
You know sometimes scientific research
你知道有時候科學研究
still has some feeling of federation
還是有一些那種fation的感覺
which thing is particularly popular at a certain time
某一個時候哪個東西特別流行
I want to say I don't want to dare to be popular
我想說我不想敢流行啊
But I feel more and more
但是呢越來越覺得說
it may be the future
它可能就是未來了
if it is the future
那它如果是未來的話
of course i want to try it
我當然想要試試看
what does it look like
它到底是長什麼樣子
let me warm up
我先熱身一下吧
that's to say nothing of me stepping over the fault line
那更不用說我跨過斷層帶
What does a fault look like?
斷層到底是長什麼樣子
that just mentioned
那剛提到
All over the world if I have fiber optics in all locations
全世界如果我有光纖在所有的位置
can i put the fault under the ground
我是不是可以把地底下的断层
clearer
昧平得更清楚
I'll put the location where I know the fault first.
我先把我知道断层的位置先擺下去
Is it possible for me to go in the future?
那未来我是不是有可以去
Test other faults first
先测其他的断层
so i
所以呢我
This is actually a bit of that
这个事实上有点是那种
already know the answer
已经知道答案了
But I still want to know
但是我还是先想要了解
What does his answer look like?
他答案到底是长什么样子
so we are here
所以呢我们是在这边
Seven Star Altar Very beautiful Seven Star Altar
七星坛非常漂亮的七星坛
This is the Murren Fault
这个是米伦断层
We have a well A and a well B
我们一个井A跟一个井B
This is the upper plate This is the lower plate
这是上盘这是下盘
I want to be a control group
我想要做个对照组
Then in Well C
然后在井C呢
We measure water, air and temperature
我们是摆水跟气还有温度的量测
Do earthquake light and seismic energy detection
做地震浅照跟地震能量的探测
the real challenge is
那真正的挑战是
I'm going to take an optical fiber directly from the surface
我要把个光纖直接从地表
all the way down
一直放到下面
700 meters position
七百公尺的位置
That's a big challenge
那这个挑战其实很大
we have to first
我们要先
Of course I still have to say
当然我还要取言心
Then don't talk so much about your heart today.
那今天就不讲那么多言心的事情
That
那
that because of covid
那因为COVID的时候
I play the first time swing fiber optic
我玩第一次摆光纖
To manipulate the light you have to have absolutely no folds
光线的操作你必须完全没有任何的折
Then if you want 100, it takes a day
然后你要100就要一天
One hundred to seven hundred meters in one go
一气呵成百到七百公尺
Then our approach is on Jing A's side.
那我们的做法是在景A这边
there's a light starting to come down
有一个光线开始下来
Go down to the suite
下到套馆下面
then go up
然后再往上上来
Then cross this scene A and go up and down
然后跨过这个景A上去下来之后
Go east and go to Qixing
走到往东走到七星
It's where Murren Heights is
就是米伦高地的地方
In fact, the fire department in Hualien is going to connect us now
现在事实上跟花莲的消防署要把我们连在一起
Do disaster prevention education
做防灾教育
Then go back to Scene A
然后回到景A这边
I use Chunghwa Telecom for this section of blue
我这一段蓝色是用中华电信
We had a long discussion with Chunghwa Telecom
我们那时候跟中华电信也谈了很久
So they now use our Chunghwa Telecom
所以他们现在用我们中华电信的
For our work, they are going to fight for Taiwan's sustainable award
就我们这个工作他们去争取台湾的永续奖
The first time we talked to him
我们第一次跟他说服说
How to put business work and forward-looking science together
如何把商业的工作跟前瞻的科学摆在一起
Thanks to Lin Qingren and Huang Xinhua
这要谢谢林青仁跟黄新华
They put a lot of effort into dialogue
他们花了很多功夫做对话
Chunghwa Telecom
中华电信
The main reason is that there are many houses here
最主要是因為這邊很多住家
It is also impossible for us to dig any location
我們也不可能挖任何的位置
Chunghwa Telecom
所以跟中華電信
Then he closes and continues up and down
然後他緊密再繼續往上然後往下
Then go to Qixingtan to cross the whole border
然後再到七星潭整個跨界過去
So we become a three-dimensional
所以我們就變成一個三維的
monitoring of the entire signal
整個訊號的監測
We are now writing our article
我們現在正在寫我們的文章
But we in China say that I will extend my salary
但是我們中華地方是說我去延薪
The salary extension of this special policeman actually took a lot of effort
這個專警的延薪事實上花了很多功夫
Well of course this is a long story to tell
那當然這是故事要講的講很久
If you are interested
如果各位有興趣的話
That reporter has been following us for two years
那個報導者追蹤了我們兩年
So his reporter wrote a very good article last year
所以他報導者在去年寫的非常好的文稿
And China TV News Magazine
還有華視新聞雜誌
And Dong Sen has come to make these documentaries
還有東森都有來做這些紀錄片
So if you are interested
所以各位如果有興趣的話
You can read their reports
可以看他們的報導
I just mentioned that, of course I can't say
那這個剛剛提到我當然不能說
Hit it out of nowhere
莫名其妙就打下去
Explain that at the beginning, of course, many policies
說明一開始當然做很多政策
This is after we must have done a lot of thinking
這個是我們一定是做了很多思考之後
I need to know that I'm actually certain that I'm going to fight
我要知道我打下去事實上是可以確定
about my location
我所在的位置有關
But it's not just talking about fighting
但是呢也不是說說打就打
People may not be willing to let us fight, right?
人家不見得願意讓我們打對不對
And then again in such a beautiful place as Qixingtan
然後又是在七星潭這麼美麗的地方
I went there and thought Chihsingtan is really, really beautiful.
我去那邊覺得七星潭真的是非常非常的漂亮
We hope to combine this work with sightseeing
我們希望把這個工作跟觀光是結合在一起
Combined with disaster prevention education
跟防災教育是結合在一起的
Therefore, in the selection of the whole field
所以呢在整個場子的選定
we spent a year
我們花了一年的時間
Convince Hualien County Government
說服花蓮縣政府
Disaster Prevention Office Central Disaster Prevention Office
請災房辦中央災房辦
Our director went to Hualien and so on
我們的所長到花蓮等等
do a lot of public hearings
做很多公聽會
Tell local residents why we do this work
跟當地的居民講說為什麼我們要做這件工作
It took us a year
我們這個花了一年的時間
all clerical visits
所有的文書的來訪
I am grateful that is the House of Representatives
我很感謝就是眾議院
some executives of key breakthroughs
關鍵突破的一些行政人員
and hospital administrators
還有院方的行政人員
help with a lot of work
幫忙做很多的工作
Chunghwa Telecom
還有中華電信
Chunghwa Telecom told us at the beginning that we would
中華電信一開始跟我們說我們一年要
You have to charge us 300,000,500,000 a year
一年要charge我們三十萬五十萬
1.5 million in three years
三年就一百五十萬
I want to say we don't have the funds
我想說我們沒有這個經費
So we convinced a lot
所以我們說服了很多
tell him why
跟他講說為什麼
what do you think about this
你覺得這件事情
Chunghwa Telecom
對你們中華電信
is also worth it
也是值得的
So it took a lot of work to have this conversation
所以花了很多功夫做这方面的对话
So thanks to the many teams and all the observations in the field
所以感谢很多团队还有在现地的所有的观测
This whole thing took about a year to start earning
这整个大概花了一年的时间才开始赚
Start earning, of course the key is of course very big
开始赚当然关键当然很大
is when we reach earning generation
就是我们达到赚成代的时候
I have been worrying together all the time
我是一直一起一直以忧啦
We took the exam for two months
我们整个考赚考了两个月
When I took the exam, I thought it was great.
那考赚的时候我觉得说太好了
It should be that we reach Earn Generation
应该是我们达到赚成代
But at the same time, I feel that I can't make money, what should I do?
但同时我觉得说我赚不下去了怎么办
At that time, it was said that the hospital's plan was to talk about it.
那时候说在院方这边的计划讲说
Mr. Mao, your knowledge rate is too low
毛老师你的知识率太低了
You need to finish it quickly
你要赶快执行完毕
So there's a lot of dialogue probably with the colonial side
所以有很多对话可能有跟殖民这边
or the office on this side of the courtyard
或是院的这边的办公室
Quick Technician does a lot of dialogue
快技师做了很多对话
i can't give up
我不能放弃
But it was impossible for me to give to the money-making company the year before last
但是我前年不可能给赚钱公司
I have to be in place before I can give
我一定要到位我才会给
Then this is fiber optic
那这个的话是光纤
too much on this story
这个故事上也太多了
I will tell the result directly
我直接讲结果
This is the fiber that actually runs from the UK
就是这光纤事实上从英国
COVID is very serious
COVID非常的嚴重
So when his instrument comes
所以他的儀器來的時候
We put it in the middle of the situation for two months
我們就先放在中情放了兩個月
no one dares to touch it
沒有人敢去動它
The British company is coming
那英國的公司要過來
found the company
發現公司過來
We've spent all the money the madman cleared.
我們單單狂人清的錢就全部都花光了
It's impossible to make money from negative companies
這不可能讓負面公司的錢
so by us young people
所以是由我們年輕人
Ph.D. Dr. Gu Jinshang
博士 古今上博士
And these drilling teams
還有這些鑽井的團隊
step by step to design
一步一步去設計
Because when I take the whole case
因為我整個case一下的時候
fiber next to me
我旁邊放光纖
I can't fold the fiber
我光纖不能折到
But I want very good copying
但是我要非常好的copyling
Then I'm going to fix it really well
然後我要非常好的固定
So the whole technique has been practiced N hundred times
所以整個技術是延練了N百次
That is, every step we take every step to achieve
就是我們每一步每一個步驟都達成
Then I thank the British team
然後我很謝謝英國的團隊
at christmas time
在聖誕節的時候
he is video chatting with us
他在跟我們視訊
Our optical fiber was launched in December last year
我們這個光纖是在去年的12月
It should be the year before last
應該是前年了
December 31
12月31號
That's really the first signal coming in
那真正第一個訊號進來
is January 1, 2022
是2022年的1月1號
We are all welcoming the sunrise at Qixingtan
我們都在七星潭迎接日出
In fact, there is no place to live
其實都沒有地方住
Because Qixingtan is full
因為七星潭已經客滿了
So we are in fact
所以我們事實上是
Everyone find a place by themselves
大家自己找地方
to finish but just happy
去完成 但是就是很高興
When the signal is completed
訊號一完成的時候
But Taiwan is not worried about earthquakes at all, the signal will come in immediately
但台灣完全不愁地震 訊號馬上進來
ok then this is
好 那這個是
Scene A on January 1, 2022
景A在2022年的1月1號
Scene B on June 2, 2022
景B在2022年的6月2號
In other words, June 2, 2022
也就是說2022年的6月2號
Our entire circuit is complete.
我們整個的回路算是完工了
That is, as soon as we put it down,
就是我們一擺下去就是
Must be all 24 hours at once so
一定要24小時馬上全部 所以
And put all the wiring together
還要把所有的線路擺在一起
is the completion of our entire signal
就是我們整個的訊號的完成
follow the operation
跟操作
I think it's really about the signal of an earthquake.
我想真正應該是講地震的訊號
That's what it said
那這個就是提到說
Yes, all the work, is it worth it?
對 花了這麼多工夫 它到底值得嗎
I've actually been thinking
我其實一直在思考
for what
for what
my signal is beautiful
我的訊號很漂亮
At that time this was
那時候這個是
You see, it starts to go down on January 1st.
你看1月1號開始擺下去
I face the computer every day
我每天都在對著電腦
The earthquake on January 7, an earthquake in Taichung
1月7號的地震 一個台中的地震
I think earthquakes are really good
我覺得地震實在是太好了
Because it has a scale of 4.7, it is neither too big nor too small, and it is very deep.
因為它規模4.7 不大不小 又很深
So its signal to our station is almost vertically rounded
所以它的訊號到我們的車站幾乎是垂直入舍的
I saw this signal and thought it was so beautiful
我看到這個訊號覺得美麗的不得了
but i mean earthquake repair
但我是說地震修
so i feel very beautiful
所以我覺得非常的美麗
This is from the ground to the ground
這是從地表到景下
then it is symmetrical
然後它是對稱
I just told me to go down
我剛講我下去
then up again
然後又上來
you can see it's symmetrical
你可以看到它對稱
then you can see
然後你可以看到
This is a two-second signal
這個只有兩秒的訊號
I can see when the batch comes in
我可以看到批播進來的時間
Then I've seen some disturbances in these
然後我已經看到這些一些擾動
These disturbances are seismic zones
這些擾動都是地震帶
fault zone
斷層帶
then i see some facial zone
然後我看到一些facial zone
I am one and then how does the seismic wave reflect the selective shot
我一個然後地震波如何反射擇射
I can see everything clearly
我全部都可以看得清楚
Even so
就算是這樣子
I'm still staring at it in a daze
我還是對著它一直發呆說
So what can you do?
So what can you do?
Ok
Ok
You guys beautiful and then
You guys beautiful and then
so I've been thinking about it
所以一直在思考這件事情
But there are more and more important discoveries
但越來就越有一些重要的一些發現
For example this is the same as an earthquake
例如這個是一樣的一個地震
Of course I drew it in a better way
我當然用比較好的方式去畫出來
you can see
你可以看到
4 meters, sorry, forgot to mention
4公尺 对不起 忘了讲
we are one
我们是一个
We have a resolution of 4 meters
我们是4公尺就一个解析度
Then the signal is 1000Hz
然后讯号是1000Hz
So it has a very, very large amount of data
所以它资料量非常非常的大
Of course we have to treat it as
那当然我们要把它当
When sample to 200Hz
当sample到200Hz
Then we also follow what we get
然后我们也跟我们所得
The grid center of our courtyard
我们院方的网格中心
Thanks to Mr. Liang Wenzhong
要谢谢梁文忠老师
They have collaborated many times before
他们以前很多合作的
on some basis of
的一些基础上面
Do this same conversation with the grid center
跟网格中心也做这一对话
Our data is sent to the grid center
我们资料是传到网格中心
Then our grid center has
然后我们网格中心在有
When we analyze data
我们在分析资料的时候
Put data directly from the center of the grid
直接从网格中心把data
extract
萃取出来
then this part is
那这个部分是
Collaboration between many units in the hospital
院这边很多单位互相的合作
then we
那我们
An earthquake is coming up from below
一个地震是从下面上来的
You can see this signal below
你可以看到这个下面的讯号
It's standing in a row, it's quite beautiful
是排排站 算是蛮漂亮的
After reaching the fault, it was disturbed
到了断层之后就受到了扰动
then you have surface reflection
那你有地表反射
Then your batch comes in
那你的批波进来
your signal
你的讯号的
The structure of each signal and formation
每个讯号跟地层的构造
Can simulate one by one
可以一个一个做模拟
for real
真正的
don't do any analysis at all
完全不要做任何分析
You can see where it says I'm close to the fault line
你可以看到说我靠近断层带的位置
The whole government is amplified
整个政府就放大了
remember what i just mentioned
那記得我剛剛提到的
Cheung Chau flag shakes near fault
靠近斷層的長洲旗震動
In this example it is
以這個例子來講就是
you don't move anything
你什麼東西都不動作
you actually see it is fault behavior
你事實上看到它就是斷層的行為
it doesn't happen randomly either
它也不是隨機發生的
As long as your fault zone is certain
只要你的斷層帶是有一定的
The difference in material
材質上面的不同
it produces a government amplification
它會產生政府的放大
fault zone
我們可以把斷層帶
not very clear
沒評得非常清楚
about 20 meters
大概是20公尺
Then this is a fault zone only 20 meters
那這個是斷層帶只有20公尺
So, if you take Jinxia earthquake today
所以呢你今天如果把錦下地震
you'll miss it too
你一樣會錯過它
because after you cross the fault zone
因為你過了斷層帶之後
It behaves exactly the same
它的行為就滿一致的
So you can only rely on this very high resolution
所以呢你只能要靠這種非常高的解析度
Only then can you know if your long fingers have been magnified
你才可以知道說你長指有沒有被放大
Did you really see the Yanpan signal?
你是不是真的看到延盤的訊號
Going back to the beginning of the earthquake just mentioned
回到剛剛提到的地震的一開始
0.01 seconds how long is it
0.01秒它在長怎樣
If you look at it from a shallower position
你如果從比較淺的位置來看
it has been disturbed
它都已經受到干擾了
what you really want to see is
你真正要看就是
You have to start looking at the Yanpan signal
你要從延盤的訊號開始看
This is what we now want to continue to
這也是我們現在想要繼續在
Inquiry, if I detect a magnitude 1, magnitude 2 earthquake
探究的 我如果偵測到一個規模1 規模2的地震
Its initial signal that it is certain
它的一開始的訊號 它是有一定的
Hold on to the relationship on the road to explore
持路上的關係去做探討
that this
那這個
Of course, there are many discussions about fault generations.
這當然講斷層代代有很多討論
For example say I am in my three months
例如說我在我三個月
This fault generation was mentioned in the AGU seminar in the United States
在美國的研討會AGU裡面在提到這個斷層代
Then many people must want to say when did you see this fault generation
那一定很多人想說 你什麼時候看到這個斷層代
The most important value of this job is that we can also gain
那這個工作最主要的價值就是我們還取得言心
This word heart is just a double stare after I take it in.
這個言心就是一翻兩瞪眼 我斷層拿進去之後
I took out Yanxin and could see very fine fault mud
我把言心拿出來可以看到 很細的斷層泥
Just mentioned that it's stuck all over the drill
剛剛提到說它整個卡鑽
Our drill bits are actually very hard, even diamond bits
我們的鑽頭事實上是很硬的 甚至是鑽石的鑽頭
But because this has been informed to Nano, there is a lot of water
但是因為這個已經到奈米的告知 有很多水
So when my drill goes in, the whole
所以我的鑽頭一進去的時候就整個
You just cover it all up so my drill bit can't move the hole at all
你就把它整個包住了 所以我的鑽頭根本連洞都動不了
So the whole technical thing
所以整個技術上的東西
It took about two months
大概花了兩個月的時間
Then I also think our Taiwan team
那我也覺得我們台灣的團隊
The engineering team is also very strong
這個工程團隊也是非常強
He also understands that our work is a scientific challenge
他也了解我們這個工作是科學挑戰
so he is not in a hurry
所以他也不急著
But he is also in a hurry
但也是很急他
Because they still have a lot of geothermal greed projects to implement
因為他們還有很多地熱貪堪的計畫要執行
he mentioned
他提到說
Mom, teacher, if you don't continue to specialize
媽媽老師你這個不繼續專下去的話
I'm about to be fined again for my civil service plan
我公務院的計畫我已經又要被罰了
because I'm tired
因為我已經抵累了
But thank you all for some support
但是謝謝大家的一些支持
This is very important. It can be seen from the heart.
這個是蠻重要的在言心上面可以看
Of course the words
那這個言心當然
The same is that you can publish many top-level articles
一樣的是可以發表很多篇的頂級的文章
because the behavior of the entire fault zone
因為整個斷層帶的行為
It depends on these territorial studies
是要靠這些領土地學去看的
Then these are some English students of my summer vacation
那這是我暑假幾個英文的學生
This is Lai Xuanrong, he told me he would come today
這是賴軒榮他有跟我說他今天會來
then during the summer vacation
那麼暑假的時候
Let's look at some data from Taiwan for several months
我們看一些台灣幾個月的data
you can see the fault line
你可以看到斷層帶
Every earthquake he is a continuous amplification
每個地震他就是持續的放大
The location of this fault zone
這個斷層帶的位置
Then see Decay on the surface
然後看到地表什麼的Decay
But the upper plate has a relatively large magnification
但是上盤有比較大的放大
It's Decay
就Decay了
So at that time, I often said that you bought a house
所以那時候常常講說你買房子的
Be sure to buy the lower order, don't buy the upper order
一定要買下盤 不要買上盤
that of course means
那當然就是說
You need to know where your upper plate is and where your lower plate is
你要知道你的上盤在哪裡 下盤在哪裡
that or
那或者是說
But Taiwan has many faults
但是台灣因為斷層很多
So the footwall on your side may be the hanging wall of another fault.
所以你這邊的下盤可能是另外斷層的上盤
So the standard of the whole struggle is the real
所以整個的抗爭的標準才是真正的
place to analyze
要分析的地方
But this is very important to understand
但是這個是很重要的理解
then you fault
然後你斷層帶
When you get close, you see your whole government zoom in
靠近的時候 你看你整個政府放大
abnormally long
破常變長
But on the sidelines the whole thing changes
但是在旁邊整個破常就改變了
So this is actually
所以這個事實上是
We are talking about this change in history
我們在講這個歷學上的變化
That's as far as we mentioned back then
那遠正我們那時候提到說
A scale as small as this is 20 meters
像這麼小的尺度是20公尺
So of course small earthquakes we can see very clearly
所以小規模地震我們當然可以看得很清楚
But the far positive signal comes in for a few seconds
但是遠正的訊號進來是數秒鐘的訊號
That is, my wave is already a signal of more than 10 seconds
就是我的波已經是大概是10秒以上的訊號
how can i still see it
我怎麼還可以看到呢
but we're far away
但是我們在遠正的地方
still see it zoomed in
依然看到它放大
That's the article we're writing right now
那這是我們現在正在寫的文章
just to explain
就是了解說
The reason for this magnification is actually the material of the fault zone itself
這個放大原因事實上是斷層帶本身的材質
It's Lumps constant
它的Lumps constant
when changes occur
產生變化的時候
It has some government amplification factors in it
它是多了一些政府的放大的因子在裡面
This part is very important to say
這個部分就很重要的地方是說
We've been talking about earthquake induced
我們一直在講說地震誘發
I don't know if you guys mentioned it on the news
我不曉得你們各位有沒有在新聞上提到說
After the Great East Japan Earthquake
好像東日本大地震之後
Earthquakes all over the world turned into gunpowder
全世界地震都變火藥了
Also, after the Sumatra earthquake and tsunami in 2004
還有那時候2004年的蘇門達大地震海嘯之後
Everyone has heard that earthquakes all over the world seem to turn into gunpowder
大家聽到說全世界的地震好像都變火藥
The reporter asked
那記者就問說
Teacher Meng, do you think this is related?
盟老師你覺得這有關聯嗎
Let's say it's a different board
那我們就說這是不同的板塊
But in fact, we actually feel in our hearts that
可是事實上我們心裡其實覺得說
Indeed its behavior is amplified
確實它的行為有放大
That's why we haven't found the theory
那可是我們還沒有找到學理
But when working with this
可是以這個工作的時候
I think it's a good inspiration to say
我覺得非常好的啟發是說
So no matter how far the earthquake comes from
所以地震不管從多遠的地方來
if you have fault
如果你有斷層的話
your strain will be magnified
你的應變就會被放大
so what
所以呢
if your self faults itself
如果你的本身斷層本身
It belongs to the critical academic situation
就屬於比較關鍵的歷學狀況的時候
you are easily induced
你是很容易被誘發的
So this is of course another article that I think can be developed
所以這當然是我另外覺得可以去發展的文章
That is, my fault zone is not just the near fault.
就是我的斷層帶不是只有近斷層
Is far positive fault I will also be excited
是遠正的斷層我也會被激發
Actually how much is it
其實它的量是多大
So maybe it can explain
所以或許可以解釋
Why the scale of the world
為什麼全世界的規模
More than eight large-scale earthquakes
八以上大規模地震
Seismic activity around the world has increased
全世界的地震活躍度的增高了
that means otherwise
那另外是說
There are many faults in our Taiwan agent
以我們台灣代理斷層很多
so i can put fiber
所以我可以放光纖
can see some signals
可以看一些訊號
but to europe
但是對歐洲
or to other countries
或是對其他國家
Earthquakes are not as active as we are
地震沒有像我們這麼活躍
but they still need to know
但是他們還是要知道
where is the fault
斷層在哪裡的話
If he puts the optical fiber
他如果擺了光纖
He doesn't have to wait for the earthquake next to him
他不用等他旁邊的地震
Earthquakes around the world
全世界的地震
he has a chance
他就有機會
Know where his fault is
知道他斷層在所在的位置
So this is what I think is a
所以這是我覺得是一個
very important application
非常重要的應用
That's Chunghwa Telecom
那這是中華電信
Chunghwa Telecom's signal
中華電信的訊號
Of course not as beautiful as we thought
當然沒有像我們想的那麼美麗
because it is along
因為它是沿著
The ditch goes like this
航溝這樣子走的
but
但是呢
We've been doing analysis with them
我們一直在跟他們在做分析
but you can see
但是你可以看到
But our job is to see some
但我們的工作是看到一些
enlarged
放大的
Continuous zoom position
持續放大的位置
This is actually the same as our wild
這事實上跟我們野外的
The tomographic magnification position is the same
斷層放大位置是一樣的
So Chunghwa Telecom's signal
所以中華電信的訊號
Our future challenge is to
我們未來的挑戰就是
how do i put him
我如何把他
It works by applying the above
它應用上面的工作
business work
商業上的工作
applied to our science
應用到我們科學上面來
Then there are these reflections on the surface and so on.
那還有地表這些反射等等之類
I think this might be too thin
我想這個可能太細了
that real other job
那真正的其他的工作
For example, how did my fault break?
例如說我斷層到底是怎麼破了
Like the March 22 earthquake
像3月22號的地震
I have a total of small earthquakes
我一共小規模地震
I can work out the mechanics of massive earthquakes
我可以把大規模地震的力學做出來
this is what we do
這是我們在做
inside a fault
就是一個斷層裡面
This is the same from the bottom to the top
這個一樣從最下面到最上面
i can every second
我可以在每一秒鐘
I saw a patch
就看到一個patch
That is to say, above the fault level
也就是說斷層面上面
it actually has several
它事實上是有好幾個
The so-called patch is composed of
所謂的patch所組成的
Then each patch
然後每個patch
There will be the possibility of the signal from Cheung Chau
就會產生這個長洲起訊號的可能性
This is another scientific challenge
這也是另外一個科學的挑戰
It is because when we did the analysis in this area before
是因為以前在做這方面的分析的時候
They all use signals from Cheung Chau
都是用長洲起的訊號
The previous signal took about 2 to 30 seconds
就以前的訊號大概是用2到30秒
2 to 30 seconds
2到30秒
P-POS 6 kilometers per second
P-POS 6公里每秒的話
Your resolution is 10 km
你的解析度就是10公里
so you'll see our fault line
所以你會看到我們斷層帶的
Calculation is very smooth
計算都是非常平滑的
with current mechanics
那以現在的力學
With the signal of the present light now
以現在現在光線的訊號
I'm up to 1000Hz to
我是到1000Hz到
This is a direction signal at least 200Hz at 200Hz
這是200Hz的至少200Hz的方向訊號
I can map every piece of every piece
我可以把每一塊每一塊都Maping出來
Then we are working with Captain now
那我們現在跟Captain那邊在合
it's my mechanics
就是我的力學上面
how do i break from one piece to another
我如何從一塊破到另外一塊
after the earthquake
就是我地震發生之後
Going back to how the earthquake happened
回到剛剛提到地震是怎麼樣發生
its a cascadia act
它是一個Cascadia的行為
If it encounters a relatively large Stress
它如果碰到一個比較大的Stress的時候
It's about accumulating energy around here
它是讓能量在這附近累積
Then on a Patch I just mentioned
然後在就我剛講的一個Patch
It actually continues to break forward after accumulating energy.
它事實上是在累積能量之後再繼續往前破
to what extent is it accumulating
那它在累積到什麼樣程度的時候
it will stop
它會停下來
That's what I think the light is about.
那這也是我覺得這個光線的資料
future available jobs
未來可以提供的工作
But I'm talking on paper now
但是我現在都是紙上談兵
All I can say right now is that I see the signal
我現在只能是說我看到這個訊號
I'm thinking
我心裡在思考
Inside the new Generation
在新的Generation裡面
what can we do
我們可以做的工作是什麼
Then of course I hope I have a chance in the future
那我當然希望我未來有機會
verify my ideal
驗證我的理想
Of course the same
那當然同樣的是
Earthquake early warning work
地震預警這些工作
its whole signal
它的整個的訊號
actually huge
事實上是很龐大的
So it is absolutely necessary to use the technology of AI
所以絕對必須要用到 AI 的技術
Because we have a way to wait until we take it one by one
因為我們有辦法等到一個一個慢慢看
So how do I use whatever Visualization
所以我如何用不管是 Visualization
That is, I use images to directly respond to the strain
就是我用圖像式的直接去應變
Or when the documents come in, I will scan them first.
或者是資料進來的時候我就直接先去掃描
Do training in this area
做這方面的 training
This is our work combined with big data
這是我們跟大數據資料結合的工作
And how to analyze the coupling of the entire data, etc.
還有這整個的資料的 coupling 如何分析等等
It's all done step by step
都是一步一步要執行的
So I'm probably going the easy way today
所以我今天大概是簡單的方式
Let me introduce to you the coming of this light generation
跟各位介紹這個光世代的來臨
But I don't know if I really have the means to achieve my ideal
但我不知道我是不是真的有辦法達成我的理想
But I think it's a start
可是我想它是一個開始
Then at least the key to this technology
那至少這個技術的關鍵
Work on current energy, green energy, etc.
在現在能源 綠能等等這方面的工作
Initiative work can be produced
可以產生一個起發性的工作
Then our place is very beautiful
那我們的場子非常的漂亮
Welcome to Qixingtan when you are free
歡迎各位有空到七星潭
Then our place, I also hope that it will become a work of education.
那我們這個場子我也希望說變成是教育的工作
Then
然後
Today a seminar in Japan is held here
今天一份日本的一個研討會在我們這邊辦
We will also do these related discussions here
我們也會在這邊做相關的這些討論會
I hope this is a start
我希望這個是一個開始
Then last week, I know that some units have already visited
那在上個禮拜我知道有些單位都已經去看
I want to know how they're going
想要瞭解說他們到底要怎麼擺
It is currently technically feasible
那目前這技術上是可行的
I also hope to have more opportunities to share with you
那也希望更多機會跟各位分享
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, we are very grateful to Mr. Ma Guofeng for giving us
好 我們非常謝謝馬國豐老師給我們
such a brilliant speech
這麼精采的演講
Indeed, Qixingtan is a very beautiful place.
的確七星潭是一個非常漂亮的地方
If you have ever been
如果大家有曾經去過的話
then we start now
那我們現在就開始
Open to questions on site
開放現場的提問
In particular, I want to announce that
那特別要宣布一下就是
Top 10 Questions
前面10名提問的
audience friends
觀眾朋友
You can get a 9-pound flat souvenir
可以得到一個9斤平的紀念品
here we are
在這邊我們
Secretariat staff will
秘書處工作人員會
will be delivered to you
會送到您的手上
ok so now everyone
好 所以現在請大家
Raise your hand if you have any questions
如果有問題的話 請你舉手起來
Then you have a microphone in front of your desk
然後你的桌子前面有一個麥克風
The problem with pressing the microphone down
把麥克風按下去的問題
we can all hear
我們就可以大家都聽得到
ok sir please
好 那位先生請
i have a lot of questions
我有好多問題
But first I ask two questions
不過我先問兩個問題
The first question is the fault just mentioned
第一個問題就是剛才講的斷層
Our intuition in signaling
我們直覺在信號學裡面
basically a resonance
基本上是一種共振
It seems that there is no so-called resonance problem on the fault side.
那斷層那邊看起來好像沒有所謂共振的問題
i don't know if
我不知道有沒有
but we have another problem
但是我們有另外一個問題
Cascade just mentioned
剛才講的Cascade
That is to say it has something of this wave that it reflects
也就是說它有一些這個波的東西它會反射
So there's an exposure wave and there's a reflection
所以有一個露射波也有一個反射
reflection in reflection
反射在反射
So it could very well turn into a so-called positive backtracking
所以它很可能變成一個所謂的正回溯
Positivity of the feedback
Positivity of the feedback
Make it taller than that Embed to
讓它變得那個Embed to的變高
I don't want it, right?
我不要的對不對
But it is interesting to say that the fault
但是很有意思就是說這個斷層的
This looks like its Mesh is that quality
這個看起來它的Mesh就是那個質量
It seems like these problems are resonating with
看起來好像跟共振這些問題
Or the NPU becomes larger
或是NPU變大
It seems that it doesn't matter much
好像看起來關係不怎麼大
But I'm curious, so let's find out
不過很好奇 所以了解一下
The second question is that I ask first
第二個問題是我先問一下
have a question about communication
有關於通訊的問題
You only rely on Fiber or sending signals
你只依賴Fiber或傳送訊號
Does it look like it's still being used?
看起來是不是還有利用
Other communication systems are doing the dissemination
其他的通訊系統在做傳播
because actually
因為其實實際上
I happened to be in Dulan for the earthquake in Chishang
池上的地震我剛好在都蘭
I'm actually standing on a board
其實我是站在一個板子上面
i fell
我是摔下來的
But we are not afraid of earthquakes
但是我們並不怕地震
Because there is a distance of 1 kilometer between the residents there
因為那邊住戶跟住戶之間差1公里
so you just look at that
所以你只要看那個
Seems like it won't fall off
好像住子不會掉下來
you won't run
你都不會跑的
i mean
我的意思是說
Fiber laid by Chunghwa Telecom
中華電信所鋪的Fiber
It's actually on the East Coast on Coastal Highway 11
其實在東岸在海岸11號公路
It's actually pretty bad
其實是很差的
That is to say, the transmission rate
也就是說那個傳輸數率
is bad
是很差的
so you put Hualien
所以你放著花蓮
I think Qixingtan may be a good location
我覺得七星潭可能是一個不錯的位置
The question is how to manage it
問題是怎麼去manage它
So I guess the part about the newsletter
所以我想關於通訊的部分
I want to ask here to compare
我想就問到這裡比較
Thanks
謝謝
ok i'll be the first to mention
好 我先第一個提到
The incident wave you just mentioned
你剛剛講的這個 incident wave
reflection
reflection
reflection is completely simulated by us
reflection 完全我們是都可以模擬的
So the three-dimensional vibration simulation just mentioned
所以剛剛提到那種三維震動模擬
just doing
就是在做
So in terms of the fault zone
所以以斷層帶來講
is all our trip waves
就是我們所有的 trip wave
That is, I may have a signal in it
就是我可能會有訊號存在裡面
Then of course it was previously thought
然後當然就是以前認為
Government Amplification of the Fault Zone
斷層帶的政府放大
May be caused by trip wave
可能是 trip wave 造成的
Then our current analyst sees that
那我們現在的分析師看到說
In fact, it is caused by the difference of materials
事實上是材料的不同造成的
Of course it may also appear as a trip wave
那當然它 trip wave 也可能會出現
just say our biggest key
只是說我們最大的關鍵
It's not just a trip wave
不是只有 trip wave 而已
this is one
這是其一
Then if you briefly mention
那如果再簡單提到
the signal you just said
你剛剛講的那個訊號
it's two things
這是兩件事情
We just use fiber optics as a tool
我們只是把光纖當作一個工具
The transmission of the signal depends on
訊號的傳達還是靠
Wi-Fi
靠 Wi-Fi
or
或者是
Of course, the two elders have just
當然兩老是有剛剛的
see it near you
看到它就在你附近的位置
The data of our Proband
我們Proband的data
some even rely on artificial satellites
都有一些是甚至靠人造衛星
on various
就各種不同的
Then we just talked about Chunghwa Telecom's fiber
那我們現在剛剛講中華電信的fiber
Not all fibers can be used
也不是所有的fiber都可以用
If you're that kind of Black Fiber
如果你是那種Black Fiber
In fact it still doesn't work
事實上還是不行的
So you have to go to fiber optic 5G
所以你必須要到光纖5G的
part like this
這樣子的部分
Therefore we now
因此我們現在
Chunghwa Telecom is in Midas
中華電信就是在Midas擺的是
fiber optics
我們自己擺的光纖
because I'm going to the depths
因為我要到深度的時候
I have to resist temperature and pressure
我必須要抗溫跟抗壓
So my fiber optic is actually
所以我那個光纖事實上是
Not affected by temperature and pressure at all
完全不會受到溫度跟壓力的干擾
then we just want to say
那我們只是希望說
If it is really going to be popularized
如果真的要推廣到普及的話
We can't do it all by ourselves
我們不可能全部都我們自己擺
So we're going to use the commercial
所以我們要用用看商業的
that commercial
那商業的
He can't do it for us
他也不可能為我們而做
So we have to strike a balance in the middle
所以我們必須要在中間取得平衡
So his Maintain is completely
所以他的Maintain完全是
commercial company
商業的公司
Maintain themselves
他們自己Maintain
Our future cooperation of course
我們當然未來的合作
hope is to say
希望是說
I know
我知道
Two researchers in China and ancient and modern times
中華跟古今上兩位研究員
They also have a relationship with Chunghwa Telecom in Taipei
他們也跟中華電信在台北市有一段
Because you know some of Chunghwa Telecom's grids
因為你知道中華電信它的一些網格
Not every paragraph can be used
並不是每一段都可以用
because you must have a loop
因為你一定要有個迴路
They first try a circuit for analysis
他們先試用一個迴路做分析
it's the same
也是它的一樣
Tell him about our negative life here
對我們的負值命在這邊跟他講說
very expensive
很貴
They want 300,000 a month
他們要一個月要30萬
then we feel
那我們就覺得說
what am i going to try
我到底要試
Can I try it for a week?
我可不可以試一個禮拜就好了
don't try for a month
不要試到一個月
But this is in a speculative stage
但是這是在一個揣摩的階段
So I just said
所以剛剛才要說
These fibers on the East Coast
對東海岸這些光纖
Chunghwa These cables may not work yet
中華這些電纜可能還不能用
but we're talking about the future
但是我們是說放於未來
Because the optical fiber in the future must be better and better
因為未來的光纖一定是越來越好
Probably the simple answer is this
大概簡單的回答是這樣子
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
we'll follow
我們就接下來
ok that one is behind
好 那位在後面
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Because it means 5.5 and above will have that
因為是說5.5以上才會有那個
Is that the transmission tube?
那個那個傳管播嘛
It's an emergency signal.
就是通知大家緊急信號
then again
那然後又是
if you are in
如果說你是在
If it is located in Zhenyang
位在那個鎮陽的話
you won't
你根本就不會
when you get the signal
就是你接到信號的時候
you already happened
你已經發生了嘛
Does that mean that if
那是不是表示說如果
feel an earthquake
感覺到已經發生地震
then heard the signal
然後才聽到那個信號
that means this
那表示這個
I am facing this
我現在面臨的這個
This earthquake will be severe
這個地震會是很嚴重的
Duality will also be more serious
對偶也會是比較嚴重
this means
這個意思
That's right.
確實也是這樣子沒有錯
right
對
but
但是
I must say that now we are doing
我必須說以現在我們在做
The so-called method of earthquake prevention and disaster reduction is
所謂的防震減災的方式是
Just a little shock
就小震
Nothing will happen to Xiao Zhen
小震就不會怎麼樣
Moderate earthquake
中震
A moderate earthquake, a major earthquake, etc.
中震的大震不倒之類
such a concept
這樣子的概念
is how we keep our defenses on cover
就是我們如何讓我們防護在蓋的時候
Even if it is an earthquake resistance specification
就算是耐震規範
There is no way to meet such a large standard of resistance
沒有辦法達到抗爭的這麼大的標準
but it's slanted
但是它是傾斜的
instead of whole crushed
而不是整個crushed
It's not like the whole building of the pseudo-officials fell down.
不像偽官大樓這樣整個倒下去
The man has absolutely no hope of surviving.
那人完全沒有存活的希望
but
但是呢
It is impossible to make it infinitely superior to the earthquake resistance code
耐震規範也不可能讓它無限上綱
So because it still has some cost considerations
所以因為它還是有一些成本的考量
So it is indeed a means of earthquake early warning
所以確實地震預警它是一個手段
But it's not entirely possible to do all the work around
但是它不是完全有辦法做所有的解決
Shock resistance is still important
耐震還是重要的
That's why I said
所以才會說
We're talking to the Ministry of the Interior
我們跟內政部這邊在講
old house reconstruction etc.
老屋重建之類的
When I mentioned it to the Ministry of the Interior, I found out that
跟內政部在提的時候發現說
Many units actually
很多單位其實
That is, they put about 3 billion yuan for earthquake resistance
就是他們放了大概三十億做耐震
Earthquake resistance assessment but no one came to apply
耐震評估但是都沒有人來申請
There is no one to apply for the reconstruction of the old house
老屋重建沒有人來申請
That of course starts with everyone's information
那當然就是開始大家的資訊上面
They think that if I apply today,
他們覺得說我今天如果去申請的話
Am I not here without shadow three hundred taels?
我不是此地無影三百兩嗎
Say later that my house is not good
待會兒說我的房子不好
That's the concept we're pushing
那這是我們正在推的概念
Just like all of you here
就是像在座你們各位來一樣
just say
就說
In fact, the disclosure of information allows everyone to do things more bravely
資訊公開事實上是讓大家可以更勇敢的做事
Because when your information is not public
因為你資訊不公開的時候
you actually grow
你事實上是長著
when it grows
那長著的時候
Everyone doesn't even know where it is
大家就更不知道到底著在哪裡
so i can come up with a solution
所以我可以提出solution
So I think the point now is to
所以我覺得現在的重點是
I face it when I can make it public
我可以把資料公開的時候我去面對它
then we can make it better
那我們就可以把它做得更好
that's what we're talking about risk management
就是我們在講的風險管理
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好謝謝
ok let's see if there is any more
好我們再看看還有沒有
this gentleman
這位先生
Hello Mr. Ma
馬老師你好
I know this plan is his from the 2018 earthquake
我知道這個計畫就是他從2018年地震
start after the shock
震完之後開始去
to explore
去探專
In fact, speaking from the public's point of view, it means that everyone
那其實在民眾的角度來講的話就是其實大家
An earthquake in the southern part of Canada will be like destroying the city of Liujia
會對加南地區的地震像是六甲斷城
Central axis structure
中軸構造
this kind
這種
He will also be me in the next fifty years
他未來五十年之內這也是我
I refer to Mr. Ma's information
我參考了馬老師的資料
His chances are very high
他的機率非常的高
Will you talk about this plan in the future?
那未來會不會說這個計畫
The faults that will be transferred to other places to make carbon bricks
會轉移到其他地方的斷層去做碳磚
For example, put fiber optic bricks into the hexagonal fault
比如說把光纖磚到六角斷層裡面
Thanks
謝謝
I think so, but it's a big challenge
我是這麼想 但是實在挑戰很大
When I published
我那時候在發表的時候
when i publish
我在發表的時候
middle school teacher said
中生大學老師說
Ma, when are you coming to Jiayi?
馬老師你到底什麼時候要來加益
this
這個
This Labr has a lot
這個Labr量很大
but it's really my idea
但是真的是我的構想
Even we originally hoped to go to the Meishan fault
就是我們當初也希望去煤山斷層擺
Where is the Meishan fault?
煤山斷層到底在哪裡
Actually it's still not clear where it is
事實上目前還是搞不清楚它到底在哪裡
someone said
有人說說
Did it go into the mountain or not?
它到底有沒有到山裡面等等
The Tainan Earthquake of 1852 on the Hexagonal Fault
六角斷層1852年的台南地震
It may be related to the hexagonal fault
可能是跟六角斷層有關
150 years now
現在已經150年了
next to it is chinese reservoir
它旁邊是中文水庫
so in fact it does
所以事實上確實
this is a start
這個是一個開始
we hope for the future
我們希望未來
don't even need us to show
甚至不用我們擺
Using Chunghwa Telecom's signal
用中華電信的訊號
way to understand where his fault might be
辦法理解他斷層可能所在的位置
but i have to buy the ambassador
但是我必須要買那個大使
the ambassador itself is expensive
大使本身很貴
Thank you for your support
謝謝遠方的支持
The ambassador wants 7 million to 10 million
大使要七百萬到一千萬
but it is potable
但它是potable的
That means I can spend two months here today
也就是說我今天可以在這邊擺兩個月
Then go to another place for two months
然後在一大別的地方去擺兩個月
that this is now
那這個是現在
but we currently feel
但我們目前覺得
Because ambassadors are becoming more and more commercially competitive
因為大使越來越商業競爭越來越厲害
So the price goes down every year
所以價格就每年往下降
because everyone knows
因為大家都知道
After it is very important, many manufacturers have begun to appear
它很重要之後很多廠商都開始出現了
So maybe there's a chance in the future
所以或許未來有機會
Can be more decoration
可以更多的擺設
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
we have no other
我們還沒有其他
Casual good
隨便的好
this one is behind
這位在後面
please turn on the microphone
請你開開麥克風
Mr. Man, I have no problem.
蠻老師我沒有什麼問題
but i want to say thank you
但我很想跟你說謝謝
feel so hard
覺得好辛苦
I just stopped all the way feeling sad
我剛剛一路停下來覺得很心酸
that is
就是
Thank you
謝謝你
is what we do
就是為我們做的事情
But I do have a doubt
但是我確實有個少疑
because we're an earthquake nation
因為我們是一個地震國家
why are you doing this part of the research
為什麼你們在做這部分的研究
He is a great contribution to the country
他對國家是一個非常大的貢獻
But why so little money
可是為什麼經費這麼少
I just feel sad the more I listen to it
就是越聽越覺得很難過
but i want to say
但是我都想說
say thank you
跟你說謝謝一下
Thank you
謝謝你
Thank you for your recognition
謝謝你認理切
try to
盡量
It's okay
也還可以啦
At least the hospital has supported us in this project
至少院方有支持我們做這個計畫
The matter of large-scale earthquakes
大規模地震這件事情
In fact, I have been talking for more than ten years
事實上是我講十幾年
At that time, the vice president just mentioned
那時候剛剛副院長有提到
sort of telling a story
有點在講故事
But the vice president mentioned that
但是副院長有提到說
I started TEM Taiwan Earthquake Past Life
我開始TEM台灣地震前世
I'm actually in the hospital
我事實上在院方
we will write a white paper
我們會寫個白皮書
At that time, Academician Liu Jiahan wrote a white paper
那時候劉佳涵院士寫個白皮書
You have to turn against the talent of engineering
跟工程的才能要翻臉
engineering say
工程的說
A certain teacher, you get out the money map
某老師你把錢事圖弄出來
No one dares to invest in Taiwan
沒有人敢來台灣投資了
because the money is so high
因為錢是這麼高
Then why do California and Japan have solutions?
那為什麼加州 日本都有辦法呢
yes we don't hide the problem
是我們不是把問題藏起來
It's about what kind of situation we're facing
而是說我們到底面對什麼樣的狀況
The results of it
結果呢
The one really interested in that graph is TSMC
真正對那個圖有興趣的是台積電
So after the Tainan earthquake
所以是台南地震之後
TSMC came to us and said
台積電來找我們說
Teacher Ma, I completely follow the government's regulations
馬老師我完全按照政府的法規
Why the Beauty Earthquake
為什麼美容地震
My plant has suffered so much damage
我的廠房受到這麼大的損失
He started asking us to do a series of calculations
他開始叫我們做一系列的運算
then to massive earthquakes
然後到大規模地震
Start working with the hospital
開始跟院方這邊工作
So I think also those conversations are formative
所以我覺得也是那些對話都是有形成
Then from a scientific point of view
然後以科學的角度來看的話
is when we are ready
就是當我們準備好的時候
he can play when he can play
他可以上場就上場了
Just like a tsunami
就當時候做海嘯一樣
My doctoral dissertation is doing tsunami
我的博士文是做海嘯
My first plan is to do a tsunami in Taiwan
我的第一個計畫要做全台灣的海嘯
At the time, the National Science and Technology Council of the Ministry of Science and Technology said
當初科技部國科會說
There is no tsunami in Taiwan, why do you make a tsunami?
台灣也沒有海嘯 你幹嘛做海嘯
After the Great Sumen Earthquake in 2004
到後來2004年的蘇門大地震之後
He said Mr. Ma, you can do the math
他說馬老師你可以算一下
Tsunami potential map for the whole of Taiwan
全台灣的海嘯潛勢圖嗎
Then it will be completed within three months
然後三個月之內要完成
Of course we must also do it well
我們當然也一定也是要把它做好
So I guess it's
所以我想這是
That's the science, we're ready
科學上就是這樣 我們準備好了
When the country needs it, we want a chance to be seen
國家有需要的時候 我們就希望有機會被看到
Okay lady please turn on the microphone
好 這位女士 請妳開開麥克風
thanks thanks
謝謝 感謝
thank you thank you
謝謝 感謝你
Thank you maybe in China hope you can accept
謝謝你 也許是在中國 希望你能夠接受
ok lady please
好 這位小姐 請
Hello, Mr. Mai, I would like to ask for advice, because I am studying architecture myself.
麥老師好 我想請教一下 就是因為我自己學建築的
I don't want to say this is from the National Earthquake Research Center
我不想說這是學國家地震研究中心
Because in fact there is a that in Jingmei
因為事實上在景美那邊有一個那個
The earthquake of the one-to-one model The earthquake of the structure
一比一模型的那個地震的 那個結構物的地震的那個震
the demonstration center
那個示範中心
Then I also took students to see
那我也帶學生去看過
I want to say that the Construction Department of the Ministry of the Interior
我想說那個內政部營建署這邊
I don't know that there is cooperation with the teacher
不曉得跟老師這邊有合作
Because I think many people don’t know it’s because
因為我覺得很多民眾他不知道是因為
Say I buy a house
比如說我買房子
Are there any fault zones near Arbor
阿伯附近是有沒有斷層帶
Then I'm breaking above and below
那我是在斷著在上面下面
Just the teacher mentioned
就剛老師有提到
what is his influence on my future
他對我將來產生的影響是什麼
Especially in Taipei
尤其是臺北噴地
In fact, the commentary we just watched
事實上我們剛剛看的那個解說
Only then did I know that the spray ground has a kind of
才知道噴地它有一個那種
It is the effect of the microwave is returning
就是微波就是正回來的效果
In fact, near the 101
那事實上那個101附近
There is also a fault zone
也是有個斷層帶
so i've been talking to you
所以我就一直對你的話
For example, our sprayed ground is a mud station
比如說我們噴地是一個爛泥所
Silt formation
淤積形成
and build a house on it
然後在上面蓋房子
The assumption is that this can be molded
那假設就是這個可以成型的話
Is it possible that it's on the ACD's side?
有沒有可能在營建署那邊
When the builder develops
在建商開發的時候
Just ask him to cooperate with this academic research
就請他配合這個學術研究
He can buy an optical fiber to go down
他就可以買一個光纖下去
Well, in fact, the feedback information
那這樣事實上那個回饋的那個資料
volume will be more
量就會更多
This is my question above
這是以上我的那個疑問
Thanks
謝謝
yes thank you
是謝謝
I think so
我也是這樣想
but in actuality
但是真正在實際的時候
been challenged a lot
受到很多的挑戰
So I just mentioned that building codes actually
所以我剛剛提到建築法規事實上
Sometimes you may see some of my essays in the media
有時候你可能在媒體上看到我一些寫的投書
They mentioned that this affects investment
他們提到說這樣子影響投資
impact real estate
影響房地產
At that time I remember when I wrote an article
那時候我記得我寫的一篇文章的時候
Tell me, Mr. Ma, you will affect real estate
講說媽老師你將會影響房地產
So I said affecting real estate is something I have to worry about?
那我說影響房地產是我要擔心的事情嗎
that's not my business
那不是我的事情啊
OK, what I want to do is to tell everyone what happened
OK我要做的事情是告訴大家到底發生怎樣的狀況
So back to what we just said about the CSA
那所以回到剛剛講營證署
or the National Earthquake Engineering Center
或是國家地震工程中心
Then we probably have a lot of conversations.
那我們大概都有很多對話啦
So the National Electrotechnical Center it has the shakers now
所以國家電工中心它有現在的震動台
or Construction Department
或是營建署
I just mentioned that earthquake-resistant reinforcements have started to be planned
我剛剛提到耐震補強開始去規劃
At that time, the vice president and I were committee members of some projects.
那時候我跟副院長都是一些計畫的委員
It's the directors of the State Council, etc.
就是國務院那些的董事等等之類
we'll mention that
我們就會提到是說
how do you make information public
你如何把資訊公開
or your seismic specification
或者是你的耐震規範
Why did you spend 3 billion for example on the Menon earthquake
為什麼你花了30億例如說美農地震
I spent 3 billion to tell everyone to apply.
我花了30億說大家來申請啊
I can help you with free insights
我可以幫你做免費的見解
no one applied
沒有人來申請
There must be something wrong with the dialogue
那一定是對話出了問題
then i think step by step
那我想就是一步一步
The real ideal, of course I hope
那真正的理想我當然是希望
I'm working with another project
我跟另外一個計畫在進行
That is, I hope to place instruments in each Builder
就是我希望在每個Builder裡面都擺儀器
So back to what was just mentioned
那所以回到剛剛提到的
If I want to use the Taipei Basin
我如果要把台北盆地裡面的
If all the signals are analyzed clearly
所有的訊號都分析得很清楚的話
If I am in every
我如果在每一個
Seismographs are placed in every house
每一棟房子裡面都擺地震儀
The current price of the seismograph itself is actually
那個地震儀本身事實上目前的價位
Let me cooperate with Teacher Liang's team
讓我跟梁老師的團隊的合作
is very cheap
是很便宜的
So we can use smart things
所以呢我們可以即使的用智慧性的東西
send the signal to the user
把訊號傳到使用方
that also builds my database
那同時也建立我的資料庫
As my database becomes clearer
當我的資料庫越來越清楚
The faults in each place are enlarged and reduced
每個地方的斷層它的放大跟降低
It has a big data to do
它就有一個大數據去做
But what about building data
可是呢建物的data
no one wants to help you
沒有人願意幫你
willing to disclose
願意公開
So we now put instruments on it
所以我們現在擺了儀器在上面
but that's
但是那就是
I can let you swing
我可以讓你擺
but you can't make it public
但是你不能公開
This is also understandable
這也可以理解啦
so we are now
所以就是我們現在
The other will be with the United States and Japan
另外一個會跟美國日本
That is to say, we are going to write a white paper on
就是說我們要寫個白皮書在
because the whole world is in the same situation
因為全世界都碰到同樣的狀況
Then I know that the United States and Japan already have laws and regulations
那我知道美國跟日本現在已經有法規了
Your building is more or less new, you definitely need a seismograph
你多少都新的大樓你絕對要擺地震儀
But he didn't say to analyze the seismograph
可是擺地震儀他沒有說要分析
that's a challenge
這就是一個挑戰
If you want to analyze it, you may not have to disclose it to everyone.
那要分析他也不見得要公開給大家
OK so when we mentioned
OK 所以我們那時候提到說
Then I'll be linked to earthquake insurance.
那我要跟地震保險連在一起
if you have a pendulum
如果你有擺的話
Can you lower the earthquake insurance, etc.
地震保險你是不是可以降低等等
Therefore, many ideals and legal aspects are carried out.
所以就很多理想性跟法規面去進行
I also learned a lot
那我也學到蠻多
But scientifically, I think it can be done
但科學上的東西我覺得是可以做到的
Then the only way we can talk now is through the public sector
那我們現在唯一能夠談的方式是公家單位
If he is willing to help us
他如果願意幫我們擺的話
like this thank you
這樣 謝謝
ok, this one is at the end
好 這位在最後面
our last question
我們最後一個問題
Hello, Mr. Ma, I am here today because of the famous name.
馬老師好 我今天是慕名而來
then your speech was really wonderful
那您的演講真的非常精彩
Although I am a layman in earthquakes
雖然我是地震門外漢
But it's also delicious
但是也是聽得津津有味
Then I have a question about
那我有一個問題是關於
Muming just talked about the glamorous generation. This technology is not only
慕名剛剛講說那個光鮮世代這個科技不只是
can be used to understand faults in Taiwan
可以用來理解臺灣的斷層
It can also be used for forward-looking energy planning now
也可以拿來現在前瞻能源計畫
Technological breakthroughs in geothermal and carbon sequestration
關於地熱跟碳封存的技術上面的突破
you can specifically say
你可以具體地說
This kind of light is inside the ground
這樣子的光線在地層裡面
How can we help us break through
可以怎麼樣幫助我們突破
Now look forward to these energy
現在前瞻能源的這些
Used to go in and stop the geothermal
用作進去停了地熱
Then I think this pit is really big
然後我覺得這個坑真的很大
there are many problems to be solved
有很多問題需要解決
Then can you be more specific?
那你可不可以具體一點講說
How can this thing help this
這個東西可以怎麼幫助這個
Underground exploration
地底的探探
ok yes thank you
好 是 謝謝
I just mentioned Dust
我剛提到的是Dust
In fact, when we put the light in
事實上我們光線擺進去的時候
You can also measure the temperature directly
也可以直接量溫度
So now of course I just said it was Dust's instrument
所以我現在當然剛講是Dust的儀器
I still have a DTS instrument now
我現在還有一個DTS的儀器
I can directly measure how the temperature changes
我可以直接量溫度的變化是如何
Then my job now is to see
那我現在的工作是要看
How temperature and water affect each other
溫度跟水它是如何互相的影響
Then if the geothermal temperature
那如果以地熱當然溫度
but the important part
但是很重要的部分
Then if you are EGS
那如果你是EGS
That is, after you want to pour water down
就是你要灌水下去之後
Bring the temperature up again
再把溫度拉上來
You need to know how your water flows
你要知道你的水是怎麼流的
Although your light if
雖然你的光線如果
because of you
因為有你適合
This company is only a receiver
這公司就一個receiver嘛
So what do you get from these receivers and the government size of his vibration
所以呢你從這些receiver跟他的振動的政府大小
You can't comment on how big the water flow is
你再可以沒評出說這個水的流量有多大
and what is his direction
還有他的方向是如何
It is specific to the direction of his entire SCPG
就是具體的可以把他整個的印力方向
direction of water flow
水流的方向
But it's ideal
但這是理想性啦
This is to say that his possible application of the above work
這是說他可能的應用上面的工作
If it is carbon dioxide madness
那如果是二氧化碳瘋存
But now the situation is that he may have another earthquake
但現在碰到的狀況是他可能又發地震
Previously, the Environmental Protection Agency was mentioning these tasks
之前環保署那邊有在提這些工作
If I want to know that there will be another earthquake today
我今天如果要知道又發地震
How old will he be?
他到底會又發到多大的時候
I can actually get in with a fiber optic signal
我事實上是可以用光纖遜訊號進去之後
I do realtime monitoring
我做realtime monitoring
I only want
我只要
Because of the crazy storage of carbon dioxide, it must be pressurized into my neck.
因為二氧化碳瘋存一定要施壓到我的頸裡面
Because when I'm under pressure
因為我壓力灌下去的時候
possible recurrent cracks
可能產生又發的裂縫
So I made the crack from again
所以我從又發的裂縫
I can figure out what the size of this earthquake is
我可以算出這個地震規模的大小是多少
so i can know right away
所以我可以即使的知道說
If my earthquake reoccurs
如果我的地震的又發的次數
much more than before
比以前多很多
That is when the V value of the GRL increases
就是那個GRL的V值增加的時候
I can give direct Shutdown signal
我可以給直接的Shutdown的訊號
So our current concept is red and green
所以我們現在概念就是紅綠
The concept of red, yellow and green lights
紅黃綠燈的概念
Should be green light yellow light red light concept
應該是綠燈黃燈紅燈的概念
that's if you've been pressurizing today
就是如果你今天一直施壓的時候
Your seismic activity is not particularly high
你的地震活動度沒有特別高
Because Real Time has been on Monitor
因為一直Real Time在Monitor
So the rep said you can keep doing carbon dioxide sequestration
所以代表說你可以繼續做氧化碳封存
But when you get stressed enough
但是當你壓力到某個程度之後
Your little earthquake signal is getting more and more
你的小地震的訊號越來越多了
The representative said that your earthquake has been disturbed by you
代表說你這個地震已經被你擾動了
you may want to stress lower
你可能要壓力降低
reduce the pressure to a certain extent
壓力降低到某個程度
So that's the yellow light
所以那時候就是黃燈了
Then if its scale jumps from 3 to 4
那如果它的規模一下從3跳到4
Of course it is Shutdown
那當然就是要Shutdown了
It's you that turns into a red light
就是你就變成紅燈
That Shutdown does not mean that you will never be able to use it
那那個Shutdown並不是說你就永遠都不能用
that's what we're talking about
這就是我們現在在講的
Like the Shutdown situation caused by the earthquake in Oklahoma
像Oklahoma那邊的地震佑發的Shutdown的狀況
We mean after you Shutdown
我們是說你Shutdown之後
How long can you recover
你多久之後可以Recover
Well, this is my other idea, of course.
那這個是我當然另外的想法是說
For example, the scale of the earthquake is the scale
地震佑發的例如說規模是規模
Scale five it's probably up to magnitude five there might be some damage
規模五 它可能到震度五可能有一些損傷
That can also incorporate the concept of earthquake insurance.
那一樣可以把地震保險的概念放進來
Or the manufacturers of these energy sources
或者是說這些能源的廠商
It first places within a radius of 30 kilometers
它先把方圓30公里之內
Generally speaking, the impact of Scale 4 and Scale 5 is within 30 kilometers
就一般來講規模四規模五的影響是30公里之內的
The house is made of earthquake-resistant reinforcements to a standard earthquake intensity of five or more
房屋它做耐震補強到規震度五以上
Then use earthquake insurance to solve the problem
然後要用地震保險的方式去解決
This is what I personally think these two
這就是我個人覺得這兩個
Possible solutions for problems encountered in energy
在能源上面碰到困擾的可能的solution
Just provide a reference, thank you
提供參考就是了 謝謝
Okay, thank you all, thank you, Mr. Ma
好 謝謝大家 謝謝馬老師
because of today's time
因為今天時間的關係
we're going to end today at 8:30
我們今天要在8點半結束
Then we give warm applause again
那我們再次以熱烈的掌聲
Thank you Mr. Ma for giving us today's
謝謝馬老師給我們今天的
short brilliant speech
不長精采的演講
Thanks
謝謝
report to everyone
跟大家報告一下
our next lecture
我們下一次的講座
It is a commemorative lecture given by the former private dean
是前私量院長的紀念講座
This is co-organized with National Taiwan University
這個是在台跟台大合辦
So after the Chinese New Year on February 1st of this year in 112 years
所以在112年今年的2月1號過完年之後
Wednesday, February 1st, 10:00 am to 11:30 am
2月1號禮拜三上午10點到11點半
In the International Conference Hall of the National Taiwan University Campus
在臺灣大學校總區的思量館國際會議廳
We invited Zhen Yu and Academician from the Chinese Department of National Taiwan University
我們邀請到的是臺大中文系的鎮宇與院士
The topic we are going to talk about is polysexuality and how to be modern
要給我們講的題目是多異性與如何現代
The following explanation of this topic is
這個題目的下面的解釋是
Reflections on the Transformation of Chinese Characters in the Early 20th Century
二十世紀初漢字轉型的思考
So it's a humanities lecture
所以是人文方面的講座
Thank you again for coming today
那今天再一次謝謝大家來參加
Popular Science Lecture by Our Dean Cai Yuanpei
我們這個蔡元培院長的科普講座
Thank you again, Mr. Ma, for such a wonderful speech.
那也再次謝謝馬老師這麼精彩的演講
so have a nice night everyone
那祝大家今天有一個愉快的夜晚
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you.
Thank you.